<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pulpit sparks, or, Choice forms of prayer by several reverend and godly divines ; used by them both before and after sermons ; with other prayers for extraordinary occasions ; together with Dr. Hewytt's last prayer.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 230 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56278</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10599552</idno>
  <idno type="VID">45356</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240889266</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4203</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28464</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">10599552</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56278)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45356)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1408:39)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Pulpit sparks, or, Choice forms of prayer by several reverend and godly divines ; used by them both before and after sermons ; with other prayers for extraordinary occasions ; together with Dr. Hewytt's last prayer.</title>
                  <author>Hewit, John, 1614-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 368, [49], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Gilbertson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"By Dr. Reeve, Dr. Gillingham, Dr. Jer. Taylor, Dr. Hewytt, Dr. Wilde, Dr. Griffith, Mr. Tho. Fuller, M. Ball, M. Goddard, M. Nat. Hardy, M. Hall, M. Jo. Marston, M. Maskerness, M. Sparks."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Prayers.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45356:1"/>
            <p>PULPIT SPARKS Or Choice FORMS OF <hi>PRAYER,</hi> By Several Reverend and Godly DIVINES Used by them, both before and after SERMON.</p>
            <p>With other PRAYERS, for extraordinary occasions, TOGETHER, With Dr. <hi>HEWYTTS</hi> last PRAYER, BY,
<list>
                  <item>Dr. <hi>Reeve.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Dr. <hi>Gillingham.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Dr. <hi>Jer. Taylor.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Dr. <hi>Hewytt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Dr. <hi>Wilde.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Dr. <hi>Griffith.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Tho. Fuller.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M. <hi>Ball.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M. <hi>Goddard.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M. <hi>Nat. Hardy.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M. <hi>Hall.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M. <hi>Jo. Marston.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M. <hi>Mackerness.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M. <hi>Sparks,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>London, <hi>Printed for</hi> W. Gilbert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son <hi>at the Bible in</hi> Giltspur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>street, 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45356:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45356:2"/>
            <head>TO The Judicious, and Religious READER.</head>
            <p>THe most pious eye is that which doth look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; heaven can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be scaled with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prayer; it is
<pb facs="tcp:45356:3"/> zeal which doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish betwixt a Christian and an Atheist; we must number our comforts by the number of our ejaculations; we are not Temples of the living God if we have not our consecration by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, <hi>1 Cor. 6.19.</hi> Worship will
<pb facs="tcp:45356:3"/> save us sooner than Wisdom. If the Pulpit hath made our mortal wounds to bleed, or ake, we ought to prepare healing balsom for them in our closets. Nature is not hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled untill we bring her to her bended knees; we live mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable in wants,
<pb facs="tcp:45356:4"/> untill we do petition for a supply. We are but barren Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors, when Prayer is not the fruit of our lips, <hi>Heb. 13.15.</hi> we receive little from above, when we do not knock at heaven gates, <hi>Mat. 7.7.</hi> we understand the virtue of prayer, and yet neglect the
<pb facs="tcp:45356:4"/> duty; and we know that Prayer doth heal a land, <hi>2 Chro. 7.14.</hi> make up the hedge, <hi>Ezech. 22.30.</hi> open the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, <hi>James 5.17.</hi> and yet that we do so seldom intreat the face of the Lord, or lift up a cry, <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, 7.16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How happy might
<pb facs="tcp:45356:5"/> we be, if we would joyn reverence to our religion, ferven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to our faith, holy exercises to our holy titles! But alas the power of godliness, and the ardency of Christianity is anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quated. We might be every way wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, for we scarce seek for one blessing;
<pb facs="tcp:45356:5"/> we might burn be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, for we quench no flames above. How are our hearts hardned because we do not mollifie them by Prayer! how is Gods bosom shut, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause our lips will not open! Can those Children be looked upon as comfortable heirs, which are
<pb facs="tcp:45356:6"/> still-born? can we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect an Advocate to plead for us, when our indevotion hath silenced him? Many may doubt of their ransom, for they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver sent, or sought for it; many may despair of their feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, for they have been no earnest Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or Sollicitors
<pb facs="tcp:45356:6"/> for it; Shame to this dumb profession, hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to this unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout age. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists spend out half their lives in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, they are seldom but creeping to their Images, and kneeling before their Shrines, and we cry down su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition with secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and wil-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,
<pb facs="tcp:45356:7"/> with no wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship. Blush at their beads, beware lest their canonical hours do not make us think Prayer as some A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocryphal duty.</p>
            <p>Oh let us learn this Mother tongue of the Church; let us account our selvs but <hi>Jews</hi> outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if we cannot speak
<pb facs="tcp:45356:7"/> this language of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan;</hi> perfume Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion with these fragrant sents, for doubtless prayers are the golden Vials full of sweet odours.</p>
            <p>By prayer let us awaken torpulency, mortifie sensuality, appease conflicts, stock our selves with endowments,
<pb facs="tcp:45356:8"/> strengthen faith, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem time, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for eternity. We are most separated from the world in <hi>soliloquies;</hi> we are deafning our ears to nature, when we are crying in Gods ears; we are a kind of translated Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, when our hearts are elevated;
<pb facs="tcp:45356:8"/> we are pluming our selves with Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims wings, when we are soring a loft in prayer. Let the Saint appear in his transformed visage, let us consecrate some portion of our lives to Meditation, let us have our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stined hours to devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. We are in the
<pb facs="tcp:45356:9"/> valley of tears; some of the penitents drops, Pilgrims sighs, and wayfaring mens groans would do well. Prayer car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth in it great fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and splendour. Now that this flame may burn, I have taken some coals from the Altar to kindle it; that this
<pb facs="tcp:45356:9"/> brightness of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be resplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, I have set be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you stars in the right hand of God, casting forth their radiant beams. Here are variety of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers from variety of men rarely qualified, singularly gifted; peruse, Prize, admire, imitate: Let face an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer
<pb facs="tcp:45356:10"/> face in water. Buy this dispensato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and learn the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinal art of soul-cure, which is the fervent desire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy Christian Welwisher,</hi> Tho. Reeve.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45356:10"/>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Dr. REEVE his Prayer before <hi>Sermon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LET the words of my mouth, and the meditation of my heart, be now and ever acceptable in thy sight O Lord my strength and my Redeemer.</p>
               <p>O most glorious Lord God, in thy Son Jesus Christ our most merciful and loving Father, we miserable and wretched Sinners, dust and ashes, worms
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45356:11"/> and no men, do here in all humility of soul, prostrate our selves before thy glorious Majesty, humbly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing against our own souls, that we are a sinful Nation, a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple laden with iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, a seed of evil doers, that by our sins have defil'd our selves, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil'd our habitations, defil'd this good Land that thou hast given us to inherit, which now
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45356:11"/> groans under the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the Native sins, and is ready to spew out her inhabitants; O Lord, righteousness belongeth unto thee, but unto us confusion of face as it is to this day; for we have sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against thee; our Princes, our Nobles, our Priests, even to this our People, this whole Land, we have sinned against thee, and done amiss, and dealt very wickedly,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45356:12"/> and have added to the number of our fore-Fathers number-lesse transgressions; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstāding thou hast multiplied thy bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing upon us, having not dealt with any Nation as with us, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in many bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings and prerogatives advanced us far above the people that are round about us; but to our shame O Lord we confesse that no Nation hath been so
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45356:12"/> unthankful unto thee as we have been; for in stead of bringing forth the Fruits of righteousness and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness, we have turned all thy blessings, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and mercies into wantonnesse, so that we have been a provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of thine anger, and of thy fury, from that day that thou didst plant us here a Christian Church, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven untill this very hour; there is no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45356:13"/> no truth, nor knowledg of God in the Land, by lying, &amp; swearing, and killing, and committing A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, and by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other crimes we break out, and blood toucheth blood, and though thou hast cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led us to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Faith in thee, and thou hast re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>veal'd unto us that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>estimable treasure of thy love unto us in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45356:13"/> we have retained onely the name but nothing of the work of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, but have disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured thee in disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring of our holy calling; yea O Lord, by presumptuous sins committed w<seg rend="sup">th</seg> a high hand against thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majesty, we have crucified again the Lord of Life, we have troden under foot the Son of God, we have counted the blood of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45356:14"/> the Covenant where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are sanctified an unholy thing, &amp; have done despight unto the spirit of grace; in stead of making head against those tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and lusts that hourly beset us, by prayer calling to thee for thy grace to assist us against them, and by fasting and austere mortification, by beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down our bodies that wee might not conspire with Satan
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45356:14"/> and our own corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that betray us unto sin; we have pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perd the flesh, and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered our selves to be led Captives at the will thereof; we have not subdued or morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the works of the flesh; we have not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to cleanse our selves from all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinesse of Flesh and Spirit; we have not made a Covenant with our eyes, neither have we kept the door of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45356:15"/> our lips, but as if thou hadst sent us into this world not to serv thee but to serve our own lusts, we have been abominable in all our wayes; yea, O Lord, we have committed two great evils, we have departed from thee the ever-living God, and leaving the fountain of all blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and happinesse, in our hearts have set up the creature; we have set our affections
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45356:15"/> not on things above, but on things below, the lust of the flesh, the lust of the eyes, the pride of life, these have been the Gods that we have served.</p>
               <p>Thus have we sold our selves to commit wickedness; we have made all the members of our bodies instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of sin, and all the faculties both of souls and bodies wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of unrighteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, to obey it in the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45356:16"/> lusts thereof; yea, O Lord, thou hast found iniquity even in our holy things; we have been negligent in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of thy word, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of thy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, indevout in our Prayers, without fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency and zeal, weary of their length, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased at the returns, slothful without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertency and presence of spirit in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45356:16"/> what wearysomnesse hath been unto us in the hearing of them.</p>
               <p>Thus the duties whereby we should have been bettered in the wayes of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, thus performed, have made us worse; our very prayers have been turned into sin, and those sacrifices whereby we should have propitiated thee, have removed thee at a further distance from us; and though
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45356:17"/> thou in thy mercy and tender compassion hast opposed us in our sins, and called us to repentance, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding we have rusht into all manner of wickednesse, as the horse into the battell, and have gone from bad to worse; neither have thy judgments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wak'd us, nor thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies won us to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; we have not harkned to the voice of the Ministry, nor to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45356:17"/> the secret checks of our own Conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nor yet to the good motions of thy holy Spirit, all teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us, This is the way, walk in it, and ye shall find rest unto your souls; yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all the good means thou hast used to reclaim us, and to bring us home, we have still gon on in a stubborn course of sin, to the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of thy name,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45356:18"/> the wounding of our own souls, the scandal of others, and the increasing of that great and dreadful ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that we must one day make at the Judgement Seat of Christ; for these, O Lord, and many others of our sins, all thy waves &amp; storms have gone over us; thou hast smitten the land with a curse, &amp; ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a perverse spirit in the middest thereof;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45356:18"/> we are become a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on void of counsel &amp; understanding, a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion meated out to destruction; thou hast permitted a lying spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the mouth of thy prophets who prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy falsly, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple love to have it so; thou hast unsheathed thy Sword, thy glitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sword, and given it a charge against this land; here thou hast appointed it; thou hast given us up into
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45356:19"/> the hands of brutish men, who are skilfull to destroy, who have slain us with a rage that reacheth up to Heaven; thou hast dasht us one against an other, the Son against the Father, the Subject against the Soveraign; thou hast poured out upon us the fury of thine anger, and the strength of Battel: but yet, O Lord, that which is the height of all our sins and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45356:19"/> and the great demonstration of thy wrath upon us, we are so farre from being humbled under thy heavy hand, that we are not sensible of it; thou hast kindled a fire and it burneth, yea it burneth us, and we lay it not to heart, nor consider that it is an evill thing and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thing that we have departed from the Lord our God, and his fear is not in us;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45356:20"/> woe unto us, we have pulled away the shoulder, we have stopt the ear that we might not hear, we have made our hearts harder than the Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant, and the nether Milston impregnable; for all thy judgments, have not peirced us, nor made those im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions of compun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction &amp; sorrow which are the end wherefore thou diddest send them; so that as our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45356:20"/> spots are not the spots of thy Children, so we have just reason to fear the judgments un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which we groan are not the Chastise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a loving fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but of an angry Judge; we have too just reason to fear thy Judgments under which we groan, they are not a wind to fan and to purge us, but a whirlwind to scatter and utterly to destroy us, as if the sentence
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45356:21"/> were already past and the decree gone forth, as if our dayes were at an end because the shadowes of the eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning are so far stretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out; but yet oh Lord be not weary of thy repentings; though thou hast been prest under the load of our sins, be not angry with us for ever, but in the midst of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment remember mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; though the tree be barren, yet let
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45356:21"/> not the decree go forth to cut it down; let not the decree go forth, but spare us good Lord, spare thy people whom thou hast redeemed with thy most precious blood, and be not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with us for ever; though we have kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a fire in thy anger, yet let it not burn to our utter destruction; thou art a God of mercy and compassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, pardoning iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45356:22"/> transgression and sin, oh pass by the transgression of the remnant of thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, enter not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Judgment with us, passe by the iniquity of this Land, say not unto this land and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thou hast no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in it; but, O Lord, hear the prayers, look upon the tears, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the sighs and the groans of those that intercede, and, O Lord God, grant a gracious
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45356:22"/> return of our prayers, and return once more, we beseech thee, thy old returns, thy old mercies and thy old lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindnesses both to Church and people.</p>
               <p>And now, O Lord, having powred out unto thee our soules in the humble confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of sins under which we stand guilty before thee, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come humble suters unto thee for grace to preserve us from sin
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45356:23"/> for the time to come; for without thy grace preventing us, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but sin; visit us therefore, oh Lord, w<seg rend="sup">th</seg> thy salvation, that we may live undefiled in the way of thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and see the felicity of thy chosen, and rejoyce and give thanks with thine inheritance; to this end send thy holy Spirit into our hearts, to teach us to deny ungodliness and flesh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45356:23"/> lust, that we may live righteously, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and soberly in this present world, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that we are to make at the last day; oh let it subdue every thought and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that shall exalt it self against the Scepter of thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and bring it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to obedience un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee; give us, we beseech thee, either peace from temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45356:24"/> or victory over them: in all assaults of our Ghostly Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, let thy mighty hand have prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence and bring migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty things to passe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven victory and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance unto thy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, that so by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance of thy Holy spirit we may crucifie the old man, mortifie the works of the flesh, subdue our corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, vanquish Satan, and triumph over the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45356:24"/> powers of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of darkeness; O put thy fear into our hearts, that we may never depart from thee; put thy love into our hearts, that our lukewarmnes being raised up to the flames and fervency of Cherubims, we may love thee above all things, and loving thee above all things we may fear to offend so good and so gracious a God.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:45356:25"/>
               <p>And now, O Lord, we become humble suters unto thee for the good estate of the remnant of thy holy Catholique Church, dispersed far and wide over the face of the whole Earth: more especially be gracious to that part yet left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst us in these Kingdomes; as thou hast planted it in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and poverty in the death and passion of thy Sonne Jesus
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45356:25"/> Christ, so didst thou water it with the blood of thy Apostles and Martyrs, and she still continues a Lily among the Thorns, she still wears the Crown of Thorns, and purple robe, she took from the Head, &amp; side of her dearest Lord; but yet O Lord, though thou hast made afflictions the portion of thy Children, though thou dost give them the bread of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45356:26"/> makest afflictions their portion, feedest them with the bread of tears, and givest plenteously of tears to drink, yet in the midst of Judgement remember mercy, we beseech thee; deliver not up the soul of thy Turtle Dove into the hāds of the multitude of her enemies, but hedge her about with thy mercies, protect her by a custody of Angels, confound her
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:45356:26"/> enemies; confound the devices of those that are risen up against her, let not heresy cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt her doctrine, or Schism profane her worship, nor liberti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nism dissolve her dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, nor sacrilege invade her portiō, but deck her Priests, by what Names or Titles soever they be called, with health, then and then only shall her Saints sing with joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullness; be gracious
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:45356:27"/> we beseech thee and mercifull to all those that are any way af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted either in soul or body, or state, or all; more especially be gracious we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee to these thy servants who have recommended them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to our prayers; make thou their bed in all their sickness, sanctifie their afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons unto them, lay no more upon them than they are able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:45356:27"/> bless we beseech thee all those means that thou hast ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, if it be thy wil restore them to their former health; speak but the word and they shall be healed; if they shall exchange life for death, give them all grace fit for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditiō, wash them with the blood of thy Son Jesus Christ, that he may be unto them both in life and death
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:45356:28"/> advantage. Lastly we come unto thee for our selves here assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in the Courts of thy house to hear &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thy holy word; O Lord, it is thine own ordinance, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be present with me that am to speak; thou hast ordained the weak things of the world to cōfound the wise; magnifie thy power in my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; thou that hast the key of <hi>David,</hi> that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penest
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:45356:28"/> and no man shuts, open my mouth that I may shew forth thy praise; open the hearts also of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation here present that with fear and trembling they may hear and receive thy holy Word; that I preaching, and they hearing, we may all study to express it in life and conversation, to the glorifying of thy name, the edifying of our brethren, and to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:45356:29"/> the salvation of our souls, in the great and terrible day of the Lord Jesus, in whose name, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Dr. <hi>Gillingham</hi> his prayer before Sermon.</head>
               <p>O Lord God whose power is infinite, and purity such that cannot endure the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding any thing that is unclean; how
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:45356:29"/> should we that are forlorne dust, and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full flesh, presume or dare to present our selves before thee? When we look on the vileness of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the sinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of our lives, we cannot chuse but cry out and say, Woe unto us, we are undone, for we have been men of polluted lips; The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry prayers we make to crave pardon for our sins, are stayned in the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:45356:30"/> uttering, and must needs ad to our trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression, if in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or justice thou shouldest weigh or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine them; but O Lord thou art a God of infinite compassion, that wouldest not the Death of a sinner, but that he be converted &amp; Live; thou hast not only allowed us, but commanded us to call upon thee, in all our troubles and distress<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; thou hast promised
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:45356:30"/> that at what time soe- a sinner doth repent him of his sins, thou wilt put away all his iniquities out of thy remembrance; In obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience therefore to this thy command, and in confidence of this thy promise, we are bold at this time to appear before thee, renouncing all merit, and trust, and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and affiance in our selves, and relying only on thy mercy &amp;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:45356:31"/> the Soveraign media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, in whom only thou art well pleased, and through whom thou canst not be offended with us. O Lord hear thine own Son for us; O Lord hear thine own self in us, that blessed Spirit of thine, which makes interces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion for us with groans and sighs that cannot be expressed. Pardon and forgive all our
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:45356:31"/> sins, both Original and Actual; of Omis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion or Commission; of thought, word, or deed; of Ignorance, infirmity, or presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which we have at any time commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted against thee; nail them to the Cross of Christ, that they may never rise up in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment against us either to shame us in this world, or condemn us in the world to come; bury them in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomless
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:45356:32"/> Sea of thy mercy and forgetfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, that they may never appear before thee to hinder thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours unto us; Seal the remission of them to our Souls and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, that they may not distract or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturb us in our devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and crush and subdue the rebellion of our natures, that they may no longer reign in our mortal bodies; and having
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:45356:32"/> cleansed and purified us from all spots and stains of Sin, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech the O Lord to pour thy grace and holy Spirit into us, that may enable us to walk before thee in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness, &amp; in righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, &amp; in sobriety all the dayes of our Lives.</p>
               <p>We are members O Lord of that mystical body whereof thy Son Christ Jesus is the head, and therefore are sensible of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:45356:33"/> of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church; we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull unto it, and to every member of the same wheresoever dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persed, howsoever di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stressed, or by whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever despised tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowout this universal World; oh Lord call them that are yet strangers, and have not heard of thy name; reduce and bring home those that are gon astray &amp; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:45356:33"/> raise up all that are fallen, and confirm and strengthen such as do stand; bind up all that are broken, and heal all that are bruised; unite us all in soundness of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine by the Spirit of Truth, in holiness of life by the Spirit of Sanctification, and in brotherly compassion &amp; Christian affection by the Spirit of Love.</p>
               <p>O Lord, we beseech thee to open the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:45356:34"/> of thy mercy, and to pour out of thy ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derest compassion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all such as mourn in our Sion; many are the troubles of thy poor saints and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and thou only knowest how to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them out of all their troubles; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther therefore any be inwardly distressed in soul, mind, or consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or outwardly afflicted in body, estate or good name, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:45356:34"/> thee give them speedy ease out of their misery, or pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to endure what thou shalt be pleased to lay upon them.</p>
               <p>And more we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee to open the eyes of these thy sick servants who desire at this time to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to our prayers; Oh thou that art the God of health, and sender of sickness, sanctifie this thy visitation unto
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:45356:35"/> them; make their Beds in their sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, lay no more up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them than thou wilt give them strength and patience to bear, and if it may stand with thy graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous will, grant that they may recover their former health to do thee service here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; but if thou that knowest what is best needfull for them hast determined at this time to take them
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:45356:35"/> or any of them unto thy self, O Lord we beseech thee to fit and prepare them for the hower of death; give them a true sense and feeling of their sins, and a lively apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of thy mercy in Christ Jesus, that so surely repenting of the one, and cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laying hold on the other, they may with confidence and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort resigne up their souls into the hand of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:45356:36"/> thee their most merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Creator and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</p>
               <p>And lastly we come unto thee for our selves gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the fear of thy holy name to hear and handle thy holy word; oh Lord thou hast or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained preaching to be an ordinary means for the Salvation of our Souls, give a bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing therefore to this thine own ordinance; open my lips that my
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:45356:36"/> mouth may shew forth thy praise, and open the ears and hearts of this present congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, that with meek hearts and due reverence, they may hear, receive, believe, and practice thy holy word, to the glory of thy name, and salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our souls, and that for our Lord and Saviour Christ Jesus sake, in whose blessed name and words we conclude these our
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:45356:37"/> imperfect prayers, as he in his holy Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel hath taught us, saying; <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Dr. <hi>Jeremy Taylor</hi> his Prayer before <hi>Sermon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Eternal God, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Jesus Christ, Lord, and Soveraign of all the Creatures, we though most unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:45356:37"/> by reason of our great and innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble transgressions, yet invited by thy essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Goodness, and Commandement, do with all Reverence, and humble confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, approach to the Throne of Grace, begging of thee for the passion of our dearest Lord, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move our sins, as far as the East from the West, and to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them no more, lest
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:45356:38"/> thou smite us in thy jealousie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume us in thy wrath &amp; indignation, which we by heaps, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugations of sin, most sadly have deserved to feel, and sink under to eternal ages.</p>
               <p>For we confess (O God) to thy Glory, who so long hast spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red us, and to our own shame, who so long have resisted, &amp; despised so glorious a mercy, that we are the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:45356:38"/> vilest of sinners, and the worst of men, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the world, and neglecters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and undervalue its interests, being passio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate for trifles, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different for eternal treasures; weak to serve thee in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural powers, and not careful to imploy, and to improve the aides of the Spirit. We are proud, and envious, lustful, and intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, prodigal of our
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:45356:39"/> time, and covetous of money, greedy of sin, but loathing Manna the Bread that came down from Heaven. Willing we are to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any thing, or to do any thing, to please our senses, and to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie Ambition, or to purchase the world, but are neither wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to do, or suffer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny contradiction for the cause of God. In prosperity, we are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent, and proud;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:45356:39"/> In adversity, pusillani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and cowardly; ready to promise any thing in the day of our calamity, but when thou bringest us to comfort, we forget our duty, and do just no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. We are full of inconsideration and carelesness, desirous to be accounted holy by men, but careless of being approved so to thee our God. In all our conversation we are uneven, soon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbed,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:45356:40"/> quickly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, not quickly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peased; petulant, and peevish, and disorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a whole Body of sin, and evill is our portion; w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are Heirs of wrath, infirmity, and folly; shame, and death is our inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>But O God, thou art our Father, gracious, and merciful; thou knowest whereof we are made, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brest that we are but
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:45356:40"/> dust. Be not wrath very sore, O Lord, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remember our iniquities for ever, for we are ashamed of the sins we have desired, and are confounded for the pleasures we have chosen; O make us penitent, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, careful as the watches of the night, that we may never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the folly wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we are now asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but that in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:45356:41"/> we may serve and please thee all our dayes, working out our salvation with fear and trembling.</p>
               <p>O Lord, Father, and Governour of our whole life, leave us not to the sinful counsels of our own heart, and let us not any more fall by them. Set scour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges over our thoughts, and the discipline of wisdom over our hearts, lest our igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances increase, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:45356:41"/> our sins abound to our destruction, Let our Repentance be spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and perfect, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth the fruits of a holy Conversation. Give unto us a Faith that shall never be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, a Hope that shall never make us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed, a Charity that shall never cease, a confidence in thee that shall never be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>composed, a patience that shall never faint, a noble Christian cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:45356:42"/> that shall inable us, in despite of all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, to confesse thy faith, to publish thy Lawes, and to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to thy Dispensati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to glorifie thy Name by holy living, and dying that in all changes and accidents, we may be thy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and thou may'st take delight to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don us, to sanctifie us, and to save us, that we may rejoyce in the mercies of God, in the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:45356:42"/> day of recompences, at the glorious appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus.</p>
               <p>Bless O Lord, thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Catholick Church, with all blessings, and assistances of thy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and Providence: Let the daily sacrifice of Prayer, and Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rist never cease, but for ever be presented unto thee, united to the Intercession of our Lord, and for ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail for the obtaining
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:45356:43"/> to all her Sons, and Daughters, grace, and blessing, pardon, and holiness, perseverance, and glory.</p>
               <p>In particular, we humbly recommend to thy Care, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, thy afflicted handmaid the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Thou hast humbled us for our pride, and chastised us for our want of Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. O forgive us all our sins, which have provoked thee to arm
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:45356:43"/> thy self against us. Blessed God, smite us not with a final and exterminating Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Call not the watchmen off from their Guards, nor the Angels from their charges; let us not dye by a famine of thy word and Sacraments; If thou smitest us with the rod of a man, thou canst sanctifie every stroak, and bring good out of that evill: But nothing can make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:45356:44"/> to us, if thou hatest us, and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferest our souls to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish. Unite our hearts, and tongues; Take the Spirit of Error, and Division from us, and so order all the accidents of thy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, that Religion may increase, and our Devotion may be great, and popular, that Truth may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged and promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp; thy Name glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, and thy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:45356:44"/> instructed, and comforted, that the Spirit may rule, and all Interests may stoop, and obey, publish, and advance the Interests of the Lord Jesus.</p>
               <p>In order to which end, we pray thee to look down in mercy upon thy servants, and where thou hast pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Right and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority over this Nation, give the supreme and choycest of thy blessings,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:45356:45"/> health, and peace, strength, and victory, a long and a prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Government, a Portion in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Grace here, and glory hereafter, through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
               <p>Give a double por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy Spirit, to the Ministers of the Church, the Dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers, and Stewards of the Holy things of God; Grant that by a holy life, and a true
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:45356:45"/> belief, by well doing, and patient suffering, by diligent, &amp; sincere Preaching, and assidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prayers, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries, they may glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thee, the great lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of souls, and after a plentiful conversion of sinners from the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of their way, they may shine like the Stars in Glory.</p>
               <p>Give unto the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of Justice the Spirit of government, and zeal, courage, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:45356:46"/> prudence. To the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, wisdom, valour, and Religious magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity. To old men, piety, prudence, and liberality. To young men, obedience, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, health, and diligence. To Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, Justice, and faithfulness. To Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks, and Artisans, Truth, and Honesty. To all married Pairs, faith, and holiness, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and sweet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliances. To all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:45356:46"/> women, the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a meek, and a quiet Spirit, chastity, and charity, patience, and obedience, a zeal of Duty, and Religion. To all that are sick, and afflicted, distressed in conscience, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted for it, give patience, and comfort, a perfect repentance, and a perfect resignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a love of God, and a perseverance in duty, proportionable comfort in this life,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:45356:47"/> and an eternal weight of Glory in the great day of our Lord Jesus. Give to all Schools of Learning and Nurse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Religion, peace, and q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ietness, power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and bou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiful Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, the blessings of God, and of Religion. To the whole Land fair seasons of the year, good Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, health, &amp; plenty, an excellent Religion undivided, undistur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, through Jesus
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:45356:47"/> Christ our Lord.</p>
               <p>Give unto us thy servants the assistance of thy holy Spirit; Grant to me to speak thy word piously, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, and with holy Intention. To these thy servants to hear it reverently, obedient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and without preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, with hearts rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to conform to thy holy will &amp; pleasure, that we living in thy love and fear, may dye in thy favour, and rest
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:45356:48"/> in hope, and rise in Glory to the participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the blessings of a blisseful immortality through the mercies of God in our Lord Jesus Christ, our dearest Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and ever-glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and most mighty Redeemer, in whose Name let us pray in the words which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self commanded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:45356:48"/>
               <head>Doctor <hi>Jeremy Taylor</hi> his Prayer after <hi>Sermon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALlmighty God, our Glory, and our Hope, our Lord, and Master, the Father of Mercy, and God of all Comfort, we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to thee the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a thankful spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in humble and joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful acknowledgement of those infinite fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:45356:49"/> by which thou hast supported our State, enriched our spirit, comforted our sorrows, relieved our necessities, blessed and defended our persons, instructed our igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, and promoted our eternal Interests.</p>
               <p>We praise thy Name, for that portion of thy holy word, of which thou hast made us par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers this day Grant that it may bring forth fruit unto thee, and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:45356:49"/> unto Holiness in our whole life, to the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thy holy Name, to the edification of our Brethren, &amp; the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Comfort of our Souls in the Day of our Lord Jesus.</p>
               <p>Have mercy on all that desire, and all that need our Prayers. Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit them with thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and salvation. Ease the pains of the sick, support the spirits of the disconsolate, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store all that are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:45356:50"/> to their rights. Remember them that are appointed to dye, Give them comfort, perfect and accept their repentance, Give them pardon for Jesus Christ his sake, that in the glories of Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty they may magnifie thy mercy for ever, and ever.</p>
               <p>Hear the Cryes of the Orphans, &amp; Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, in their calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, let all their sorrow be sanctified, and end
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:45356:50"/> in peace and holiness, in the glorification of thy Name, and the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their Souls.</p>
               <p>Lord, pitty, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, direct, and blesse, sanctifie, and save us all. Give Repentance to all that live in Sin, and perseverance to all thy Sons and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, for his sake who is thy beloved, and the foundation of all our Hopes, our blessed Lord and Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, to whom with the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:45356:51"/> Father, and the Holy Spirit, be all honour, and Glory, Praise, and adoration, now and for evermore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Peace of God, which passeth all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, keep your hearts and minds in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and love of God, and of his Son Jesus Christ our Lord, and the Blessing of God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Father, the Son, &amp; the Holy Ghost be amongst you, and remain with you alwayes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:45356:51"/>
               <head>Doctor <hi>Hewet</hi> his Prayer before <hi>Sermon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OH thou that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest the Prayers, unto thee shall all flesh come; for our help standeth in thy name O Lord which madest Heaven and Earth: therefore we beseech thee let our Prayers come before thee as
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:45356:52"/> incense, and the lifting up of our hands as an evening sacrifice; and let the words of my mouth and the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of all our hearts be now and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver acceptable in thy sight, O Lord my strength and my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>OH most glorious &amp; most powerful Lord God, whose dwelling is above the Heavens in light in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessible,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:45356:52"/> and thine eyes run to an fro to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the things that are in heaven and in earth; neither is there any thing which is not naked and open unto thee; for thine eyes are ten thousand times brighter than the Sun, beholding all the ways of men; we thy most unworthy Creatures, sinful dust and ashes, being conscious to our selves of those many foul transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:45356:53"/> that we have committed against thee in the sight of Heaven, do here hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly throw our selves down before the foot-stool of thy divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, humbly confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing besides that ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal guilt contracted by the disobedience of our first Parents, and derived unto us in our mothers womb, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we were conceived in sin, and thence brought forth in ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:45356:53"/> for w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> as soon as we were born thou mightest have fand us like chaff from off the face of the Earth into the Lake that burns with fire and brimstone, yet as if all this had not been enough to undo us, we have ever since we were born so corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our wayes, and that continually, as if we were born to do nothing else but sin: Lord, who can
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:45356:54"/> tell how oft he offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth! our secret sins, our sins of incogitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and of ignorance, and our sins of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity have defiled our souls; how much more then have we polluted them and provoked thee by sins of wilfulnesse and of malice; by sins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and against the light of grace; against thy law, and against thy Gospel; against
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:45356:54"/> thy promises, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thy threats; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thy mercies, and against thy judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; against our vowes of better obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; against the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs of thy word, against the many mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of thy grace in our souls, and against the check of our own Consciences, by slighting thy ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, neglecting thy Sabbaths, dishonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thy name, grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:45356:55"/> thy holy Spirit, bringing a scandal up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy Gospel, and our own Christian profession, injuring our Brethren, and wounding our own consciences, by doing those very things which our own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences have cōdem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned! and how much more greater art thou O God than our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, that knowest all things, that the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry best of our actions
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:45356:55"/> are sinful! for when we confesse our sins, we sin in confessing of them, and act them o're again by remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring of them with too much delight, and by speaking of them with too little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morse; and when we pray that thou wouldst forgive us our sins, we sin in praying, through deadness and dulnesse, and drowsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse of Spirit, through idle thoughts
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:45356:56"/> and wandring imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, through un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief and misbelief, so that even our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers turn into sin, that when we have done praying we had need fall down upon our knees again and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat pardon for our prayers. If thou Lord God shouldst be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme to mark what is done amiss, Lord who were able to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide it? and yet how shall we escape it? for
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:45356:56"/> whither shall we go from thy presence, or whither shall wee fly from thy Spirit? if we climbe up into heaven thou art there; if we go down into hell thou art there also; if we take the wings of the morning &amp; fly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the utmost parts of the earth, even there shall thy hand find us; if we say peradventure the darknesse shall cover us, darknesse is no darknesse with
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:45356:57"/> thee, for the night and the day to thee are both alike; seeing then we cannot fly from thee, we come unto thee, and appeal from the throne of thy just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice, unto thy mercy-seat, and beseech thee; Oh God the Father of Heaven, thou great Creator and preserv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of man, despise not the work of thine own hands; Oh God the Son that camest into the World to
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:45356:57"/> save sinners, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not our offences, neither seek thou vengeance of our sins, Lord spare us, good Lord spare thy people whom thou hast re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed with thy most precious blood, and be not angry with us for ever; Oh God the holy Ghost that despisest not broken and contrite hearts, let it pitty thee to see these thy temples our souls and bodies thus
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:45356:58"/> ruined by sin and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedness; O holy, bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, &amp; glorious Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, three persons but one God, have mercy upon us miserable sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; Sinners and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Sinners we are; teach us oh God, to grieve that we are so; give us broken and wounded spirits for all our transgressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; break these sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hearts of ours, yea take away these hearts of stone from us, and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:45356:58"/> give us hearts of flesh, that we may tremble at the voice of thy law, and melt at the sight of thy judgments and accuse and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn our selves, and be ready to joyn with thee to do justice up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our sinfull selves; but lest we should faint through the smart of the many fresh bleeding wounds which our sins have given our souls, oh do thou uphold us
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:45356:59"/> by thy right hand, and pour into our wounds that precious Balm of <hi>Gilead,</hi> a true and a lively faith in the full satisfaction that thy Son hath made to thy justice for the sins of the whole World, and through his cross and Passion, through his most pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious death and buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, through his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous resurrection and ascension we beseech thee be thou reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:45356:59"/> unto us. Lord for his sake pardon all that is past, lay none of our sins to our charge, but blot them all out of the book of thy remembrance; wash us, oh wash us throughly from our sins, and cleanse us from our unrighteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in the blood of Jesus Christ. Lord, let his blood that speaks better things than that of <hi>Abel,</hi> cry lowder for mercy
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:45356:60"/> in thine ears than do our sins for vengeance; be-sprinkle our pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted but penitent souls in the blood of Jesus Christ, that thy wrath may pass over us, &amp; that the light of thy countenance may shine upon us; seal unto our souls the free pardon and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveness of all our sins, and say unto each of our souls I am thy salvation. Oh do thou by thy Spirit assure
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:45356:60"/> our spirits that we are thy children, and that thou art reconciled unto us in the blood of Jesus Christ; and to this end work in us a detestation of all our former wickedness; help us to mortify in us all our vile and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt affections; cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify in us the old man, the whole body of sin, that we may dye unto sin, and live unto righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness. Without thee O Lord we are
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:45356:61"/> not able to do any thing, much less any thing that is good; come therefore Oh thou Father of lights, and dispel and scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from our souls the foggy mists of Sin and ignorance, that in thy light we may see light; come O thou Power of God and set up thy throne in our Souls, and sway thy Scepter there, and bring into thy sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection every high
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:45356:61"/> thought and every high imagination that exalteth it self a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thee: come O thou Wisdome of God and discover unto our Souls the folly of Sin, the vanity of the world, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulness of our own hearts; teach us we beseech thee to eschew the evil, and to do what is good: come O thou Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of God and shed abroad the love of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:45356:62"/> God in our hearts, that we may love thee our God above all things, and our neighbours for thy sake, yea our very enemies for Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ his sake, and after his example, who dyed for us when we were yet his enemies; fit us with all graces necessary for all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, with strength to resist all the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Satan, to keep our selves unspotted of the world, to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:45356:62"/> our own passions, our own vile and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt affections, with patience to bear af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and with a contented resolution to undergo whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thy hand shall be pleased to lay upon us, that whether it be in life or in death, in both we may be thine. Neither do we pray for our selves alone, but enlarge our peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to thee for thy whole Church mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:45356:63"/> here upon earth; Lord be favourable and gracious unto thy Sion the Church; let not the ungodly have their desire; O Lord let not their mischie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous imaginations prosper, But abate t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e pride, and asswage the malice, and confound the devices of all the implacable malicious enemies of thy Church and people; and of that Universe look mercifully and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:45356:63"/> compassionately we beseech thee, on that part of thy Church that thou hast planted in these sinfull Lands and Nations wherein we live: O Lord, our sins are increased a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove measure, and our iniquities are gone o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our heads, nay they are gone up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and have pull'd down thy vengeance upon our heads; for thou art wrathfully displeased with thine
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:45356:64"/> own inheritance, and thine anger is grown hot against the sheep of thy pasture; yet how long Lord wilt thou be angry? for ever? shall thy jealousie burn like fire? O remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not against us the Sins and offences of our Lives past; let thy tender mercies speedily prevent us, for we are brought to great misery; help us, O help us, O God of our salvation, for
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:45356:64"/> the glory of thy name; O deliver us and be mercifull unto our Sins for thy names sake: Lord, in the midst of judgment re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member mercy; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all our crying Sins; reverse thy fearfull though just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deserved judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that which is the most dreadfull of all judgements and continues thy judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, hardnesse of heart, contempt of thy
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:45356:65"/> word and commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: restore unto us thy wonted though undeserved mercies; send peace again in our time, O God, and let the Gospel of peace and truth flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish again in our streets, and that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually even untill thy Sons comming to judgment: let not thy scourge end in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation, nor thy wrath go on to the height of an everlasting ruin,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:45356:65"/> but O thou that takest no delight in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery of one single Sinner, spare mercifull Lord a great though a most sinfull nati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on; pitty a despised Church and distracted State; heal up those wounds which our sins have made so wide that none but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne own hands can close them; and in the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness of thy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable compassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hasten, O Lord,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:45356:66"/> hasten, we beseech thee, to put so happy an end to these wast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing divisions, that thy service may be more duely celebrated, that that authority which most represents thee which art the sole Monarch of Heaven and Earth may be most conscienciously obeyed, that the Church may be resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a true Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an unity, and these un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Realms to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:45356:66"/> their former peace; and that for his sake who is the Prince of peace, and that shed his most precious blood to purchase our peace, even Jesus Christ our Lord: O thou that art the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of peace and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of concord, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose we beseech thee all the unhappy dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and divisions that are among us; take away from all mens hearts the spirit
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:45356:67"/> of division and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, the spirit of blood-thirstiness and revenge, the spirit of pride, blindness of heart, vain-glory and hypocrisy, of envy, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, malice and all uncharitableness; and give us the Spirit of peace, unity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord; the Spirit of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, the Spirit of due obedience, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the Spirit of thy fear, that we m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y at length meet
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:45356:67"/> and live in the unity of the Spirit and in the bond of peace, and with one mouth praise thee our God; and as with one heart love one another; and as fellow-feeling members of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers miseries, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee to succour all those who in this transitory life are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with any kind of crosse, tribulation or misery; those that suffer for the testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:45356:68"/> of a good cōscience, Lord give them pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence under all their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions; make them valiant for thy truth, faithfull unto death, &amp; even in death itself, if thou shouldst call them to so great a try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and after death give them a crown of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life; and those that are under any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kind of adversity, Lord help the help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, comfort the comfortless, visit the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:45356:68"/> sick, relieve the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed, help them to right that suffer wrong, set them at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty that are in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, restore the bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, and of thy great mercy in thy good time deliver all thy people <hi>Israel</hi> out of all their troubles; and those that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to our devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we recommend to thy fatherly prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, those whom thou hast visited upon their
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:45356:69"/> beds of sickness, O Lord look down from heaven, behold, visit, and relieve those thy sick servants, look upon them with the eyes of thy mercy; O give them sure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and confidence in thee, defend them from the danger of the enemy, and keep them in perpetual peace and safety through Jesus Christ our Lord. Hear us Almighty and most
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:45356:69"/> mercifull God and Saviour we beseech thee, extend thy accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed goodness unto those thy servants that are grieved with sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; visit them O Lord as thou didst vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit <hi>Peters</hi> wives mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Captains servant; so visit, and restore to these sick persons their former health, if it be thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious will, or else give them grace so to take thy visitation,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:45356:70"/> that after this pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full life ended, they may dwell with thee in life everlasting. Lastly, O Lord, we return unto thee for a blessing upon this thine own ordinance, the handling and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thy holy word; thou hast promised that when two or three are gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in thy name, thou wouldst be in the midst of them, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form we beseech thee
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:45356:70"/> thy most gracious promise; thou only hast the key of <hi>David,</hi> that openest, and no man shutteth; open thou my lips O Lord, and my mouth shall shew forth thy praise; open the ears and hearts of this thy people, that they may hear thy word atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, keep it reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, and practise the same in their lives and conversations with a care and good consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:45356:71"/> let it be a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern unto their feet and a light unto their steps; let thy grace like the morning light of the house of <hi>David</hi> wax stronger, and corruption weaker in all of us; quicken us by thy lively and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, rowse up our inward man from this lethargy and sleep of sin; and as thou callest us from this hereditary habit of sluggishness, so pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:45356:71"/> us by thy grace, lest we double our dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease by the relapse into the spirit of slumber: so that I preaching, these hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, all of us under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing thy heavenly will, we may believe and practise the same in our lives and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versations; and all for Jesus Christ the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous sake, in whose blessed name &amp; words we farther call upon thee, as he hath taught,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:45356:72"/> commanded and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged us in his most holy Gospel, saying, <hi>Our Father &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Meditationr and Prayers for the sick by D. W.</head>
               <p>HEar my prayer O Lord, which I make unto thee upon my bed of sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness: incline thine ears unto me in this
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:45356:72"/> time of my trouble; O hear me, and that right soon.</p>
               <p>Behold thou hast made my dayes as it were a span-long, and my age though it be great in respect of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yet it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in respect of thee, for verily every man living is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vanity.</p>
               <p>My dayes are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed away like smoak, and my bones are burnt up, as it
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:45356:73"/> were a fire-brand</p>
               <p>There is no health in my flesh because of thy displeasure, neither is there any rest in my bones by reason of my sin.</p>
               <p>My wickednesses are gon over my head and are a sore burthen too heavy for me to bear.</p>
               <p>But I will confesse my wickednesse, and be sorry for my sin.</p>
               <p>O Lord be mercifull unto me, heal my
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:45356:73"/> Soul, for I have sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against thee.</p>
               <p>Call to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, O Lord, thy tender mercy and thy loving kindness which hath been ever of old.</p>
               <p>O remember not the sins of my youth, nor the offences of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per years, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy mercy think thou upon me.</p>
               <p>Cast me not away in the time of age, forsake me not now that my strength fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:45356:74"/>
               <p>Goe not farr from me, O God, my God hast thee to help me.</p>
               <p>Thou O God hast taught me from my youth up untill now: Forsake me not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in my old age, when I am gray-head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>The dayes of our age are threescore years and ten; and though some be so strong that they come to fourscore (which is a mercy wherewith
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:45356:74"/> is a mercy wherewith thou hast crowned me thy unworthy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant) yet is their strength then but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and sorrow, so soon passeth it away and we are gone.</p>
               <p>But, Lord, suffer me not to go hence in thy displeasure; O suffer not my Sun to go down in thy Wrath, nor my dayes to be shut up in the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of thine anger.</p>
               <p>But as thou art pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:45356:75"/> to bring me to my grave in a full age, like as a shock of Corn cometh in his season, so let me be gathered at last like Wheat into thy Heavenly Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
               <p>And let mine age be renewed as the Eagles in thy Kingdom of Glory.</p>
               <p>Glory be to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; to the Son, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Lord if thou wilt, thou canst make me whole.</p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:45356:75"/>
               <p>Thou in whose Hands are the Keys of the Grave and the is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sues of life and death;</p>
               <p>Lord if thou wilt, thou canst make me whole.</p>
               <p>Thou in whose alone power it is to kill, and to make alive, to bring down to the grave, and to raise up again;</p>
               <p>Lord if thou wilt, thou canst make me whole.</p>
               <p>Thou who hadst compassion upon <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:45356:76"/> Wives Mother by recovering her out of a Fever;</p>
               <p>Lord if thou wilt, thou canst make me whole.</p>
               <p>Thou who didst shew thy mercy to those Daughters of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> the Woman that for twelve yeers together was diseased with an issue of blood, and another who by the space of eighteen yeers was so bowed together, that she
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:45356:76"/> could in no wise lift up her self, thou that didst loose both these and many others from their long infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities;</p>
               <p>Lord if thou wilt, thou canst make me whole.</p>
               <p>Thou who didst re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store to life the young maiden that was dead, Lord if thou wilt thou canst restore me to my health who am an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged sinner, and a sick feeble Creature.</p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:45356:77"/>
               <p>Thou canst miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate my pains, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new my strength, and lengthen my dayes.</p>
               <p>For thou makest our beds in our sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and art the Lord of life, and health, and strength; even thou art the Almighty God and the Horn of my Salvation, O thou an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient of dayes.</p>
               <p>But, Lord, as for these outward bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings, I wholy submit my self and them unto
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:45356:77"/> thy good pleasure.</p>
               <p>If it be thy blessed will to have the dayes of my Pilgrimage prolonged upon earth, make me to live al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to thy glory &amp; to my own souls com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: as thou dost add dayes to my yeers, so do thou likewise add Repentance to my dayes.</p>
               <p>But if thou think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est it more expedient for me that I should dye than live, then
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:45356:78"/> welcome my death and dissolution, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which there is no entring into Life E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, nor hopes of being with Christ: Welcome Jesus, who by thy death hast tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en away the sting of death: Welcom that Cup, whereof thou my dear Saviour hast drunk before me, and which (even to the very dreggs) thou hast drunk off for me.</p>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:45356:78"/>
               <p>And therefore I will readily take this Cup of death, (which thou hast begun unto me) and Praise the name of the Lord. I will praise thy Name O sweet Saviour, who givest me with this Cup of Death the Cup of Salvation.</p>
               <p>I will praise thy Name who hast born all our sicknesses for us, and all our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p>I will praise thy
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:45356:79"/> name who art the Physician of souls, and callest all such unto thee as are weary and heavy laden, that thou mayst refresh them.</p>
               <p>Amongst which great number, behold me O Lord, thy poor and aged, thy sick and weak servant; weary in my bones, and laden with my sins.</p>
               <p>But Lord I come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee in obedience to thy call; and of
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:45356:79"/> those that come unto thee thou castest none out. Lord, I come unto thee for Ease and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshing.</p>
               <p>O my Beloved Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jesus, in the midst of the weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of my body, in the midst of the load and burden of my sins, in the midst of the sorrowes which are in my heart, O let thy Comforts and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solations refresh my Soul.</p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:45356:80"/>
               <p>And when the snares of Death com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe me round about, let not the pains of hell take hold upon me. But by all the Merits of thy Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, Death, Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and Ascension, I beseech thee to seal unto me (in thine own precious blood, and by thy most holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit) the full pardon of all my sins, and to admit me who am thy own Purchase to
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:45356:80"/> a Participation of thy Glory.</p>
               <p>Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A thanksgiving for ease in sickness, or recovery out it.</head>
               <p>BLessed be thy name, O Lord, for blessing the means which are applyed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me.</p>
               <p>It is thy hand, and the help of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that thou hast re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved me.</p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:45356:81"/>
               <p>The waters of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction had long since drowned me, and the stream of death had gone over my Soul, if the Spirit of the Lord had not moved upon these waters, and led me forth besides the waters of Comfort. O spread, O most gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God, as thou hast, thy hand upon me for a Covering; and also enlarge my heart with thanksgivings or thankfullnesse, and fill
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:45356:81"/> my mouth with thy praise.</p>
               <p>Praise the Lord, O my Soul, and all that is within me praise his holy name, who hath saved thy life from destruction, and crowned thee with mercy and loving kindness.</p>
               <p>Grant Lord that what thou hast sown in mercy, may spring up in duty.</p>
               <p>Let my duty and returns to thee be so
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:45356:82"/> great as my needs of mercy are.</p>
               <p>O let thy grace so strengthen my purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, that I may sin no more, lest thy threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning return upon me in anger, and thy anger break me in pieces. What am I O Lord? what is the life and what are the capacities of thy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, that thou shouldest do thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me?</p>
               <p>Praysed be the Lord
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:45356:82"/> daily, even the Lord that helpeth us, and poureth his benefits upon us.</p>
               <p>He is our God, even the God from whom cometh salvation; God is the Lord by whom we escape death.</p>
               <p>In the midst of the sorrowes which were in my heart, thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts O Lord have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshed my Soul.</p>
               <p>It is thou O Lord who hast made my flesh and my bones to rejoyce.</p>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:45356:83"/>
               <p>Behold, happy is the man whom God cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth; therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spise not the chasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of the Almighty.</p>
               <p>For he maketh sore and bindeth up; he woundeth &amp; his hands make whole.</p>
               <p>In the midst of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he remembreth mercy.</p>
               <p>Lord, thou hast lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up the light of thy Countenance upon me.</p>
               <p>Yea Lord thou
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:45356:83"/> hast put gladness into my heart; O, be thou graciously pleased to put thankfullnesse therto.</p>
               <p>I will lay me down in peace, and take my rest, for it is thou Lord only which makest me dwell in safety.</p>
               <p>O Lord, I give thee humble and hearty thanks for thy great and almost miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous bringing me back from the bottom of
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:45356:84"/> my Grave; What thou hast farther for me to do or suffer, thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone knowest.</p>
               <p>Lord give me pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and courage, and all Christian Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to do thee service and grace to do it, and let me not live longer than to honour thee through Jesus Christ, Amen.</p>
               <p>Lord I have been sick and feeble, and thou hast recovered my strength; I am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:45356:84"/> aged and greatly stricken in years, yet thou art still pleased to add unto my days; Sanctify therefore good Lord the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of my life, and sweeten unto me the approaches of my Death. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Dr. <hi>Griffith</hi> his Prayer before Sermon.</head>
               <p>OH Eternal, most gracious, &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father, we are
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:45356:85"/> here come into thy house, with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, seeing that our consciences tell us, we have broke all thy Commandements, and as we have sinned in thoughts and words, in thoughts more than we can think, and in words more than we are able to express; for the number of them, that we have scarce room for any more; now we are impure, but thou of purer eyes
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:45356:85"/> than to behold iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, therefore if thou shouldst enter into judgement with us, there is not one of a thousand able to stand before thee; we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess there is but one way, to fly from thee as an angry God, but to fly to thee as a reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Father, reconciled in the bloud of thy Son Jesus Christ, to fly from the strict barr of Judgment, to thy ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der bowels of compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:45356:86"/> not according to our merits, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities, so we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beseech thee par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all our sins past, and strengthen us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all sin for the time to come, and to this end we beseech thee awaken our dead consciences, confirm our Judgments, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten our understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, conform our wills, reform our lives, enflame our
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:45356:86"/> zeal, confirm our faith, and that from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth we may live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, and serve thee, Lord give us repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance not to be repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, and that hope which will not make us ashamed, and that peace of conscience which passeth all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding; give us the world, but that world which passeth knowledg, give faith, but that faith which is in Christ, and that wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:45356:87"/> which leads us to undestanding; give us these, and all other we beg of thee, for of our selves we are not able to think a good thought, and so for thy former favours, we are altogether unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the least of thy mercies, in the behalf of thy holy Catholick Church, do good to <hi>Sion,</hi> build up the walls of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> do good in the place where we live, and we
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:45356:87"/> pray thee send in all places painfull labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers into thy vineyard; these things, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever elce thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est to be expedient for us, we beg at thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull hands, not for our own merits, but in whose blessed name we conclude as he himself hath taught us, saying, <hi>Our Father which art, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:45356:88"/>
               <head>Mr. <hi>T. F.</hi> his Prayer.</head>
               <p>LEt the Words of my mouth, and the thoughts of all our hearts be now and ever acceptable in thy sight, O Lord our strength and our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Eternal Lord God, infinite in thy greatnesse, incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensible in thy
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:45356:88"/> glory, whose pure and just Eyes cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold either sin or sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners with the least look of approbation; be not offended with thy servants; it will be little comfort for us in these glorious at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes; we come to them that may tender most consolation to us: Oh Lord God, who in Christ Jesus art mercifull and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled Father to all such sinners as sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:45356:89"/> from their Souls desire and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to repent and believe; thy provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath brought us unto this place to offer unto thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty our evening sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of prayer and thanksgiving, and to be made partakers of a portion of thy most holy Word; truly Lord we have just cause to fear les<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our prayers, instead of that blessing we now
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:45356:89"/> desire, draw down that curse which they deserve upon us; we have inflamed the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures with the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold rebellions of our lives, which have been nothing else but one constant breach of thy ten commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; true Lord, the law in our minds, our spirit, our new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, our regenerate half, our light, clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knows and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:45356:90"/> acknowledges all and every one of thy commandements for pure, and just, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but the law in our members, our dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, our flesh, our old Creature breaks them daily in thought, word, and deed; we all of us h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e been foul and fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, erecting the Idols of our own profit and pleasure in the Chapels and Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sets of our hearts, and
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:45356:90"/> then and there have fallen down upon the bended knees of our Souls, and worshipt them, by regarding our lust more than the fulfilling of thy will in thy word; that sacred name of thine whereby we hope to be saved, we have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in vain; we have done that on thy day, the Lords day, which we can justifie or avouch on no day; we have not given that
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:45356:91"/> reverence and respect to our Superiors pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced over us which thou requirest at our hands; we have brok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en all the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the second Table in our demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour towards our neighbours, and in our deportment to our own Souls and bodies; and here Lord we are ashamed to confesse the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold circumstances of our sins in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:45356:91"/> and hearing of man, who vile, bold wretches were no whit ashamed or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to commit them when we knew full well that the high God of Heaven and Earth did at that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant behold us; now lend us of thy Spirit effectually to admire at thy patience and long suffering towards us, who permits such prophane and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuous sinners at
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:45356:92"/> this hour of our lives still to remain from Hell fire; surely Lord there are many in that pit of perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whose sins against thee were never ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated with those high circumstances; O Lord, we have no variety of reasons to move thee to mercy, we have no exchange of motives to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade thee to pitty, but only the same o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and over again,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:45356:92"/> for thy own sake, for thy names sake, for thy mercies sake, for thy Son and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Christ Jesus his sake forgive our sins, for they are great; wash the guilt &amp; filth of our sins away in his blood; and Lord for the time to come give us grace to spend the remainder of our dayes in our several Callings to thy glory; Lord grant that we may not only labour
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:45356:93"/> to have our sins par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned to us, but also strive to have so much favour with thee, that before our deaths we may have our sins for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveness assured; for our comfort, grant Lord that we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take our selves to do the one thing necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; let us not have our Oyl to buy when we should have it to burn; teach us O Lord that sicknesse is a time not to do but
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:45356:93"/> to suffer; and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lord grant that our work being done, and the books crost in the times of our healths, we may be comforted when we come to dye, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe our Souls into the hands of a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Creator and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious redeemer. Blesse us with thy whole Church scattered far and wide over the face of the whole Earth; Lord, what particulars
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:45356:94"/> to pray for, we know not, we dare not, we humbly tender a blank into the hands of an almighty God; write therein Lord what thou wilt, when thou wilt, where thou wilt, by whom thou wilt, only in thine own time work out thine own honour and glory; in the mean time give us faith to believe it, patience to expect, diligence to observe, and zeal to
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:45356:94"/> pray fervently for it; to this end blesse all those whom thine own self in lawfull authority hast placed over us, by what name or title soever known unto us; blesse their counsels &amp; consulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and make them under thy self the happy instruments of the good of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Be present with us and President a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst us, at this time in the hearing
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:45356:95"/> and handling of thy holy Word; Lord let not the manifold corruptions and the more imperfections of thy servant hinder the operatiō of thy word, but give me to speak it plainly to every ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, methodically to every member, ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to every con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science that shall be here present, so that it may sink in all our hearts, and bring forth fruit in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:45356:95"/> of all our our lives and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versations. This, and what else thy wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome sees fitter for us than we can aske or desire, we beg at thy hands in the name and mediation of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ. <hi>Our Father &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:45356:96"/>
               <head>Mr. <hi>Goddard</hi> his prayer before Sermon.</head>
               <p>MOst glorious, most mighty, most holy and ever-li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Lord God, and in thy Son Jesus Christ, our gracious, merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ever-loving Father, who art the God in whom we live, and move, and have our being, who art good, and dost good,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:45356:96"/> we thy unworthy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and sinfull crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, dust and ashes, are imboldned to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before thee upon this thy day, humbly beseeching thee, for the Lord Jesus Christ his sake, that thou wouldst be pleased to accept of this our mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning sacrifice of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, &amp; praises: O Lord we come not here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee to excuse or justifie our selves, but to accuse &amp; condemn,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:45356:97"/> and judge our selves worthy of the rewards of Sin.</p>
               <p>O Lord, we do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that we are miserably sinfull, sinful in our conceptions, sinfull in our births, and have been sinfull through the whole course of our lives, and have so lived ever since we came into this world, as if we had been born for no other end but to sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thee. O Lord
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:45356:97"/> we do confesse that we have made not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the faculties of our souls, but also the members of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, instruments of sin, and weapons of unrighteousnesse; our understandings are darkned, our wills are perverse, our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are disordered, our hearts are hardned, our consciences are seared, and our bodies which should have been the Temples of
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:45356:98"/> the holy Ghost, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the cages of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean birds, and the sinks of all filthiness; our eyes are become the windows of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, our tongues the trumpets of iniquity, our hands the instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of mischief, and our feet which should have been like <hi>Davids</hi> feet, swift to run the paths of thy comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, have been too too forward to run that broad way that
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:45356:98"/> leadeth to the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of death; so that from the Crown of the head, to the soal of the foot, there is no soundnesse in us, but wounds, and brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and putrifying soars: O Lord, we have committed two great evils; we have forsaken thee, the fountain of living waters, &amp; have digg'd unto our selves ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterns, broken ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterns that will hold
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:45356:99"/> no water. O Lord, we have broken not one, but all thy holy Laws, from the first unto the last, from the greatest unto the least of them, both by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of the good duties which we ought to have done, &amp; by committing the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil things which we ought not to have done. O Lord we have sinned against all the means of grace, against thy Word, against thy
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:45356:99"/> Sacraments, against thy Christ, against thy Spirit; we have sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against all the times of grace, not only in dayes of child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and infancy, but in times of riper years, not only in dayes of ignorance when we knew thee not, but in the clear Sun-shine of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, since thy Word and thy will hath been so clearly revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unto us; and that
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:45356:100"/> not out of weaknesse, and infirmity, but presumptuously, and maliciously, against thee we have sinned, against all thy works, the work of Creation, by defacing thine I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage in us, the work of preservation, by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strusting thy Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, the work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, through un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief and infidelity.</p>
               <p>O Lord we have sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against all thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Attributes, sinned
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:45356:100"/> against thy Truth by our lying, sinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thy Holinesse by our uncleannesse; we have prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ked thy Justice, presumed too much upon thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; we have abused thy providence, and Long-suffering to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us; we have sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, which should have allured us to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; <hi>We have sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned under mercies, we have like rebellious</hi> Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:45356:101"/>
                  <hi>provoked thee at the Red Sea, when thou hast been heaping mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and blessings upon our heads;</hi> we have not only sinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst mercies, but we have sinned against thy Judgments which should have inforced us to obedience; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, thy judgements still are, and have been in our Land, yet for all this we have not learned righteousnesse, we
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:45356:101"/> have not turned unto thee our God that smitest us for our profit, for our amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but we have blessed our selves in our wicked waies, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we shall have peace, peace, though we still walk after the stubbornnesse of our hearts, adding one sin unto another: so that no means, no mercies, no promises, no blessings, no threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, no judgements
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:45356:102"/> have prevailed with us to wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k us to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to thy holy &amp; blessed will; if thou Lord shouldst en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a severe or strict account with us, we were not able to answer thee one of a thousand, but here's our com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ort, that thou hast revealed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy self to the So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of men to be a God gracious, mercifu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l, slow to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, abundant in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, not willing the
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:45356:102"/> death of a sinner, but rather that he should turn from his evil wayes and live; Oh Lord we beseech thee to look upon us, not in justice, but in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; not as we are in our selves vile by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and worse by practice; but look upon us in the face of thy beloved Son Jesus Christ, who now sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at thy right hand to intercede for poor sinners; O let the
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:45356:103"/> precious blood of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ which spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth better things for us than the blood of <hi>Abel</hi> purify us; cleanse us from all our trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions, in the pure laver of his blood; Lord wash our Souls, wash them from the guilt of sin, and from the filth of sin, and from the power of sin, and from the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of sin; Lord thou hast promised that whatsoever we
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:45356:103"/> ask in his name thou wilt give it us; it is in his name O Lord we beg at this time the free pardon and full forgivenesse of all our sins; though our sins are many and great, we know Oh Lord thy mercies are more; though our sins be like the sins of <hi>Niniveh</hi> crying up to Heaven this day for vengeance, yet we know oh Lord thy mercies are above the Heavens; though
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:45356:104"/> our sins are as red as Scarlet, thou canst make them as white as Snow; thou art a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do for us above all that we can speak or think; blessed fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we bese<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch thee to magnifie the riches of thy grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to us in the pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and forgiving our manifold sins and transgressions; the greater our sins and our miseries are, the greater will thy glory
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:45356:104"/> and thy mercy be in the pardoning &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving of such sins and of such sinners; neither do we beg thy mercy only for pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our sins past, but thy grace also for the amendment of our lives for the time to come; O Lord work in us all those graces which thou seest wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in us, and be pleased to continue and increase and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect all those graces
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:45356:105"/> which thou hast al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready begun in us; Lord if thou wilt thou canst make us clean; cleanse us we beseech thee from all filthinesse both of flesh and spirit, that we may perfect holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in the fear of God; sanctifie us throughout with thy holy Spirit both in Soul and Spirit, and body, that we may sanctifie thy holy name in righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:45356:105"/> and true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse all the dayes of our lives; teach us we pray thee to walk circumspectly, redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the time, even because the dayes are evil; and let grace we beseech thee teach us all to deny all ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse and worldly lusts, and to live so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly and righteously, and godly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent world; and Lord we beseech thee to sanctifie every crosse
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:45356:106"/> and every affliction to us, that we may be better'd by it, that we may profit under it; Lord grant that these light and momentany afflictions that are here but for a time, may cause to us an exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and an Eternal weight of glory in the highest Heavens; make us we beseech thee more and more mindfull of our latter end, of the day of judgement, and of
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:45356:106"/> that strict account we must all one day there give; minde us we pray thee of the hour of our death, and of the time of our disso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; Oh that we were but wise to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider our latter end, that we might never do amisse; and grant good God that as we do increase in days, we may increase in graces; and the neerer we draw unto our end unto our home, unto
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:45356:107"/> our Grave, the neerer we may draw to holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, to happinesse, that our last dayes may be our best dayes, our last words our best words, and our last workes our best workes; that at the end of our dayes we may all attain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end of our hopes, even the salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our most dear and precious Souls. With us Lord we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee blesse thy
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:45356:107"/> whole Church and People all the world over; call home thy antient people of the <hi>Jews;</hi> bring in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that they may be all one sheep-fold under one Shepheard. Pitty poor distressed <hi>Ireland,</hi> which hath been made a <hi>Golgotha,</hi> a place of Skuls, and an <hi>Aceldama,</hi> a field of blood; and Lord we beseech thee, look with the eye of tender
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:45356:108"/> pitty and compassion upon this divided and distracted Nation wherin we live; O that thou wouldst be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed now at last to heal the many soars, and breaches thereof, for it shaketh, O do good in thy good pleasure, to this our <hi>Sion,</hi> build up the walls, make up the breaches of this our distressed and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracted <hi>Jerusalem;</hi> teach us all O Lord, at least in this our day, to
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:45356:108"/> know things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to our peace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come to be hid from our eyes; O that there were such a heart in us that we might fear thee, and keep thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements alwaies, that it might go well with us, and our children evermore.</p>
               <p>O be not wrath with us very sore O Lord, neither remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber iniquity for ever; Lord if it be thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:45356:109"/> will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, grant once more peace and truth in our dayes. Lord, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee to blesse all those for whom we are bound to pray, and all those that do desire our prayers, and all those that do pray for us; Lord, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee hear them for us, and hear us for them, and hear the Lord Jesus Christ for us all, and be pleased to give both them and
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:45356:109"/> us all needfull graces for this and for a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter life; and O thou which art the father of mercies, and the God of all consolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, comfort we pray thee all those that are comfortlesse, all that are afflicted in Soul, or in body, or in both; all that are afflicted in conscience, or afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for conscience, all that mourn in <hi>Sion,</hi> that suffer persecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or imprisonment,
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:45356:110"/> or banishment for thy truth, and the testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science; Lord speak peace unto their Souls, supply all their wants suport them in all, their tryalls, and in thy due time give them a gracious deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, which may make most for thy glory, and for their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal good and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
               <p>Now O Lord we beseech thee to bow
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:45356:110"/> the heavens and look down with the eye of pitty and compassion upon these servants of thine which desire our prayers at this time; speak peace to their conscience, say unto their Souls, that thou wilt be their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting salvation. O Lord thou knowest their several wants &amp; necessities, draw near unto them, according to the desires of their hearts; for those that
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:45356:111"/> are sick and weak in body, make thou their beds in all the time of their sicknesse, be thou a Physician both to their Souls and bodies, heal their Souls of their sins, and their bodies of their distempers; sanctifie the sicknesse of their bodies to the good of their Souls; and bless all good means that have or shall be used, for their recovery, that they may live to
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:45356:111"/> praise thee in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest of the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but if otherwise thou hast determined of them, or any of them, Lord fit them for thine own self, and prepare them for the Kingdome of thy dear Son, that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they live, they may live to thee, or whether they dy, they may dye in thee, so that living or dying they may be thine, and that both in life and
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:45356:112"/> death Christ Jesus may be to them an advantage.</p>
               <p>Lastly, O Lord we return unto thee for a blessing for our selves here met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; O Lord, be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent both with spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker anb hearer, blesse me O Lord that am to speak; blesse these thy people that are to hear; open unto me the door of utterance that I may deliver thy word plainly, power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:45356:112"/> and profitably; open we pray thee not only the ears, but the hearts of this thy people, that they may receive the word, not as the word of sinfull men, but as the word of thee the ever-li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to save their Souls; grant good God that they may hear it at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively, conceive it readily, apply it wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, lay it up in their memories faithfully,
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:45356:113"/> meditate &amp; practise it in their lives &amp; conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions conscionably, so that it may prove to none of us the savor of death unto death, but unto every Soul here present the savor of life unto life, that hereby our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standings may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened, our hearts purified, our consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences pacified, our sinfull lives reformed, and our precious Souls eternally saved at the
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:45356:113"/> day of the Lord Jesus. These and all other needfull mercies, we beg at thy h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nds, for the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke and worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesss of Jesus Christ, the righteous, the Son of thy love, in whom thou art well pleased, in whose name and words we call upon thee. <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="210" facs="tcp:45356:114"/>
               <head>Mr. <hi>Hardy</hi> his Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Lord God, who art the wise di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sposer of all things, both spiritual and temporal, who livest in that light unto which no mortal eye can approach, and yet humblest thy self so far as to behold us thine unworthy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants;
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:45356:114"/> more especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thou hast engaged thy self by promise, to draw nigh unto, to dwell with, and to be in the midst of thy poor people, when in sincerity of heart they shall appear before thee.</p>
               <p>We therefore the unworthiest of all thy Saints, sinfull dust and ashes, worms and no men, do here in all humility prostrate our selves before thee,
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:45356:115"/> desirous to have our thoughts and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions fixed upon thine omnipresence, which beholdest us, and all within us, even the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions and dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our hearts in these holy services; as also with a confidence of thy gracious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, whereby it is that thou art in the midst of us to assist &amp; enable us.</p>
               <p>Lord, we confesse that we are unwothy
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:45356:115"/> to come before thee, to draw nigh unto thee, or to receive any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour from thee, and that because of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of our natures; we have all just cause to cry out with the Leaper, we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, we are unclean, unclean by original corruption, which like a Leaprosie hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spread all the powers and faculties of our Souls, unclean by those numberlesse
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:45356:116"/> number of actual transgressions, which throughout the whole course of our lives we have committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thee; O Lord, what have our whole lives been, but a viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy just and righteous Laws, and a neglecting of that good which hath been offered unto us? com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting much evill who might have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived much good, sinning in much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:45356:116"/> against thee in thy nature, in thy attributes, in thy name, in thy word, in thy worship; against one another in all those relations wherin thou hast put us: yea Lord, our sins have not only been multiplyed, but agravated by these cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, of love, of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and of judgement; they have been sins of a crimson dye, because too often committed
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:45356:117"/> against convictions of conscience, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the motions of thy Spirit, against the truth of thy word, against the woing of thy love, against the stroaks of thy wrath, still hardning our hearts in disobedience and rebellion against thee; yea O Lord (which makes our sins beyond measure sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) we have shut our eyes against the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous light of thy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel,
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:45356:117"/> we have cast be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind our backs thy precious promises, we have trampled under our feet the blood of thy holy covenant, and have counted it an unholy thing.</p>
               <p>In truth Lord, we come before thee day by day, as though we were desirous to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed, that we might be saved, we come to hear thy word in formality, and present our selves in
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:45356:118"/> hypocrisie, but our hearts are farr from thee, which might just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cause thee to take our prayers and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessions, our hearing and our best duties, and for ever cast them and us out of thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, because of that deadnesse, coldnesse, and dulnesse which is daily present with us in the performance of them: all our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse and our best works being as filthy
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:45356:118"/> raggs and no way able to cover us from the wrath of God.</p>
               <p>We come there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore into thy presence at this time disclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our own righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse, &amp; abhorring our selves for all our former wickednesse. And only in the name, for the merit, and through the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of our dear redeemer Christ Jesus the righteous, are we bold yet to implore
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:45356:119"/> thy mercy, to seek thy face, to sue out a pardon from the guilt of our iniquity, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire thee to be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unto us, &amp; to be welp-leased with us; O Lord, do thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get our sins, but let us remember them; do thou cast them behind thy back, but let us have them alwaies before our faces; we must confesse O Lord that thou maist glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy self in our
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:45356:119"/> confusion, and we must needs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that in the seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest of thy dispensati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thou art righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; But let our God rather glorifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in the remission of our sins, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of our natures, and salvation of our Souls: O thou father of mercy, have mercy upon us, and let all our iniquities be cast into the Sea, even into the red Sea of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:45356:120"/> blood, that so they may never rise up in judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us. O thou God of all grace, send down the Spirit of grace into our hearts, that may sanctifie us to thy service; humble us for our sin past, and establish us against sin for the time to come. Yea Lord, let us eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day grow in grace, that the house of <hi>Saul</hi> may grow weaker and weaker, and the House
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:45356:120"/> of <hi>David</hi> stronger and stronger. O give us special assistance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst our bosome sins; let them that have been the objects of our greatest love become the subjects of our deadliest ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred; let them that have been sweetest in committing, be bitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest in remembring; open our eyes that we may see our sins, and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n seeing of them let <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s beware of them,
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:45356:121"/> and in being aware of them, let us mourn for them, and in mourning for them, let us loath them, and in loathing of them, let us leave them, and in leaving of them, let us strive against them, and in striving against them grant that tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough thy grace, we may have the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry over them.</p>
               <p>Lord cleanse us from secret sins, and keep us that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuous
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:45356:121"/> sins may never have dominion over us; preserve us from Atheism and backsliding; let not that unclean spirit after he seems to be gone from us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again into any of us we humbly pray thee.</p>
               <p>O put thy fear in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our hearts that we may never depart from thee, and do thou never leave us, that so we may walk
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:45356:122"/> on from strength to strength in this valley of tears, untill we appear before thee our God; give us a sanctified use of all thy dispensations to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wards us, that sickness and health, crosses and mercies may serve as so many steps in that ladder that may carry us to Heaven; minde us of our latter end; O teach us so to live, that we may not fear to dye, that when we die
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:45356:122"/> we may be sure to live.</p>
               <p>With us extend thy compassion to thy whole Church; do good in thy good pleasure to <hi>Sion,</hi> and build up the walls of thy <hi>Jerusalem;</hi> that which thy right hand hath planted, let it be by thee preserved; O pitty the desolations of thy Church in these parts; do thou awake, put on strength in this generation, be
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:45356:123"/> zealous for the glory of thy name, the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of thy Gospel, the purity of thy truth; In thine own time, for thine own sake, by thine own means, do great things for us; plead the cause of the Widow and the fatherlesse, let the sighings of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed come before thee, supply all the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities of all thy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, give them beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for ashes, and the
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:45356:123"/> Oyl of gladnesse for the spirit of heaviness; be gracious to all that are any way distressed, heal diseased bodies, settle distracted minds, ease troubled consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, confirm weak judgements, save lost souls; we pray thee look upon those who have now desired our prayers, make all their beds in their sicknes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses; and if it stand with thy gracious pleasure, restore them to their
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:45356:124"/> former health again, and sanctifie all law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful means for that end; but if otherwise thou hast appointed for them, sanctifie them by visitation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; bind up their souls in the bundle of life, humble them for their sins, wean them from the world, let the sicknesse of their bodies be the health of their souls, that whether they live, or whether they dye,
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:45356:124"/> Christ may be unto them an advantage; Blesse them that go down to the deep and send them safety; and let those who have had former experience of thy goodness, learn still to trust in thee.</p>
               <p>And now O Lord lend the assistance of thy holy Spirit unto us thy poor servants who are here met together to hear and handle thy holy word. O remove what ever
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:45356:125"/> may be as obstacles to the power and efficacy of thy truth, knock off the bar of infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and impenitency that hath so long kept the King of glory from entring in; take away from us wee humbly pray thee, all dulnesse of mind, wandring of thoughts, drowsinesse of body, and whatsoever may intercept thy truth &amp; our profit; be in the Preachers mouth, in
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:45356:125"/> the Hearers ears, and in all our hearts; let it be delivered plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, powerfully, &amp; fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly; let it be heard reverently, meekly &amp; attentively; and let it be practised carefully, obediently and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scientiously, to the glory of thy name, the amendment of our lives, and salvation of our souls; hear us and have mercy upon us, and do more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly for us, than
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:45356:126"/> we are able to ask or think, for thy Son and our dear Redeemers sake Christ Jesus the righteous, in whose most sacred words we shut up these imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect prayers, saying,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Mr. MACHINEST his Prayer before Sermon.</head>
               <p>OH most gracious God and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Father in Jesus
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:45356:126"/> Christ; for whom have we in Heaven but thee, and who on Earth have we desired or may desire in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison of thee, whose nature is goodness, whose will is power, whose work is pitty.</p>
               <p>We humbly pray thee (pardoning our sins) to accept our prayers, and bless our labours at this time; abate my pride, and shew forth thy praise, and remedy all my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:45356:127"/> imperfections; oh multiply thy grace upon humility, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest thy power in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity; help me to plead on the behalf of thy welbeloved; and help withall this present congregation to be perswaded at the voice of my pleading; thou hast spoken by fishermen; Oh assist thy servant whom thou hast planted from a Child at the feet of the wise; out
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:45356:127"/> of the Mouths of silly Babes thou hast ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired praise, and thou hast opened the mouth of a silly Asse to rebuke the sins of a senseless Prophet; a meaner grace shall suffice me to do the like; because besides all other advantages, I feel a sting of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science and the wait of mine own iniquity, which that harmlesse Creature never felt. Only so order thou my
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:45356:128"/> thoughts in upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and sincerity; so incline the hearers minds with patience and humility, that the work which descend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of thy heavenly institution, may like wise be seconded by thy gracious operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
               <p>And in these our Prayers (Oh Lord) we are not mindfull of our selves alone (though unworthy to
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:45356:128"/> pray so much as for our selves) but farther we commend to thy fatherly protection the prosperous estate of the universall Church dispersed far and neer over the Earth, aswel her that is afflicted, tormented and persecuted in any forein or Antichris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Countrey, as this more flourishing and prospering here at home, the Realms of England, Scotland and
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:45356:129"/> Ireland. Let fall the dew of Hermon upon the two hills of Sion the two universities Cambridge and Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford. Blesse all the Nobility of this Land, teach them that ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is true Nobility, and to be thy servants their greatest glory. Blesse all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of this Land, that from the highest to the lowest we may live godly, righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and soberly in this
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:45356:129"/> present World; give them religious hearts towards thee, loyalty to their Prince and Country, and love and Charity one towards another.</p>
               <p>And in a true fellow-feeling of the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Brethren, we commend to thy favour mercy and compassion, the sick and weak estate of all thy children, of what place, in what case or under what crosse so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:45356:130"/> they be, as if we had named them all by their names; we pray thee that alone know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est them, to take com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion on their mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to ease their smart, to allay their payn, and make all their beds in their sickness; if it may stand with thy good will and pleasure, O Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store thē to their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer health &amp; strength again; but if otherwise thou hast disposed of
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:45356:130"/> them, O Lord make them fit for thine own purpose, give them a faithfull Christian departure out of this world, and a joyfull resurrection in the next; thou that art the good <hi>Samaritan</hi> pour oyl and wine into their wounds, set them on thy beast, carry them to thy Inn, and leave them not untill thou hast wrought a perfect cure upon them.</p>
               <pb n="246" facs="tcp:45356:131"/>
               <p>Lastly, we return unto thee all thanks for all mercies and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits bestowed upon us; we thank thee for our election before the world, for our creation to the world, for our redemption from the world, and for our preservation in this world; we thank thee for our pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification, sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the first fruits of our glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and all other
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:45356:131"/> hopes of a better world; yea verily Lord we thank thee for all our corrections and fatherly chastisements laid upon us, not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing our weak na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but humbling our pride, exercising our faith, trying our patience, and making way for increase of our future glory; and we humbly pray thee still to hold the same temper over us, that so living here a while
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:45356:132"/> in thy feare, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting hence in thy faith, we may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived hereafter into thy favour, and that Lord for thy name sake, for thy glories sake, and for thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy sake in Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus the best Attorney to promote a sute that we can have, in whose blessed name and words, we conclude as he hath taught us, saying, <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="249" facs="tcp:45356:132"/>
               <head>Mr. <hi>Hall at St. Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolph's Aldersgate</hi> his Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Holy Holy Holy, Lord God of Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth, Heaven and Earth are full of thy Glory, Holinesse be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth thy house for ever, thou art so infinitely pure, and holy in thy nature, that thou chargest thy Angels with folly, and the heavens are not
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:45356:133"/> clean in thy sight, thou art so infinitely dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the power of thy wrath, that thou art a consuming fire, &amp; who can dwell with ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting burnings? But withall, so infinitely gracious, and full of Compassion, that who ever trusted in the Lord, and was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded? Look down from the throne of thy Glory, in mercy upon thy unworthy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, who are here
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:45356:133"/> cast down before thee, in Fear, and reverence of thy name, to wait for thy loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, in the midst of thy Temple, Accept O Lord this day both our persons, and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, sprinkle thou us and them in the bloud of Christ, that being presented unto thee, by him our only medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, we may obtain Favour in thine eyes, and be sent away with a blessing from thy
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:45356:134"/> presence; our sins, our manifold sins, which are as a thick Cloud, to hinder the light of thy countenance from shining forth upon us, O let them be dispell'd, and scattered as a Cloud, If thou Lord shalt enter into Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with us, our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces must needs gather blacknesse, and, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it is Iniquity, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven this our solemn meeting, We ly down in our shame, and our
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:45356:134"/> confusion covereth us; O what could we have done more, which we have not done, to make thy Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie burn like fire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us? That we do not every day commit ungodliness with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinesse, not unto us, O Lord, not unto us, but unto thy preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting grace be all the praise, and yet also (prevented as we are) who can tell, how oft he offendeth? O cleā<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:45356:135"/> thou us from secret sins, Atheism and Infidelity, Irreligion and prophanenesse, Obstinacy and Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitency; Thou Lord seest the depravedness of our nature, the vanity of our mindes, the deceitfulnesse our of hearts, our weariness and Inconstancy unto any good, our prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and forwardness into all evil; Thou se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est that in the most heavenly minded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:45356:135"/> us there is a great deal of Earthly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, in the most de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout and religious much Indevotion and deadnesse of Spirit, in the most humble and mortified much vanity and spiritual pride, in the most up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pright and single-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted much doubleness and hypocrisie; O wretched that we are who shall deliver us from this body of death which doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compass
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:45356:136"/> us? Being e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way conscious unto our selves, what shall we say unto thee, O thou just judge of all men? we will take with us words, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto the Lord, and say unto him, take away all iniquity, and receive us graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously; we have sinned, but we are still the works of thy hands, and thou wilt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spise the work of thy own hands; O what
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:45356:136"/> profit will there be in our bloud, if we shall go down to the pit? we have sinned, but there is a Fountain o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened for sin, &amp; for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanness, the precious bloud of our deer Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer. He dyed for our sins, he rose again for our justification, he sitteth at thy right hand to make interces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion for us; And if he were alwaies heard, in what he prayed for, while he was upon
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:45356:137"/> earth, Is he not heard now also for us, by his infinite merits in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? We believe, Lord help thou our unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief. And O thou, in whose hands are the hearts of all men, Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate clean hearts and renew right Spirits within us; It is enough too long that we have have been servants and slaves to our own corrupt and Inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Affections, we would now hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:45356:137"/> consecrate our Bodies and Souls unto thee, and live no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to our selves, but to thy service, and Glory. That we may do so, give us thy grace (thy grace is suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for us) thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting, assisting, and following Grace, leave us not also in the hāds of our own Counsels, to our vain and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed imaginations; Take not thy holy Spirit from us, thy quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:45356:138"/> Spirit, for we are dead in trespasses, and sins, Thy inlightning Spirit, for we are full of blindness and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, Thy sanctifying Spirit, for we are full of our corruptions, that being cleansed from all filthinesse of the flesh, and spirit, we may perfect holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in thy fear; and behold, this is thy will, even our sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, that we may be presented spotlesse,
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:45356:138"/> before thee; That it may be so be gracious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleased, to take us wholly into thine own hands, to rectify and reform whatsoever thou seest amiss, and bring down every thought that exalts it self against thee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us; Give us O Lord, understandings to know thee and thy will savingly, give us devotion to seek thee affectionately, give us faith to lay hold upon
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:45356:139"/> thee, give us conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations to please thee; lead us through all the temptations, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements, through all the troubles and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements, of this present evil world, that we may keep in waies of Integrity, and Innocency, which will bring us peace at the last. And work in us we beseech thee, a Hungring, and Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting after thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse, a true zeal
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:45356:139"/> for thy glory, with a denial of our selves in whatsoever is dearest to us, a pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and breathing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy presence, as the Hart for the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of water, and that, not for the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse that flowes from thee, but for the unspeakable excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and Beauties, and perfections, which are in thy self.</p>
               <p>Hear us also O God, while we inlarge our
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:45356:140"/> prayers for thy whole Church, howsoever dispersed, distressed, and despised; yea for those also, who are without; O that thy saving light might shine forth upon those many thousand souls who sit in darknesse, and in the shadow of death, before they go hence and be no more seen. And as for these Churches of great <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> look down in mercy upon
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:45356:140"/> them; Thou O God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, dost come with healing in thy wings, and our eyes are only upon thee, to heal the sores of this land, for it shaketh, pitty all the desolations, make up all the unhappy brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, remedy all the disorders, and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, Heal all the Backslidings, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions, though they are many. Our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties do testifie against us, unto this day, yet
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:45356:141"/> thou continuest holy, and merciful. O thou who inhabitest the praises of Israel, Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble us under thy migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hand (after these terrible things, with which thou hast begun to visit us in thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness,) that wee may be more capable of thy favour, and compassion; That it may please thee, to pitty a distracted Church, and a sinful people, to heal up
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:45356:141"/> those wounds which our sins have made so wide, that none but thine own hands can cure them. O leave us not (as we have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served to be left) wrapt up in our own confusions; be thou more merciful than we have been unto our selves, supply what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever is wanting in Government, esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish what remains dissipate, and scatter scandals, stop and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:45356:142"/> all rising &amp; grow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing Heresies, make u<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> all, so far of one heart, and of one mind, that we may joyntly set our selves to the rooting up of all Atheism, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneness, superstition, faction, heresie, any thing which exalts it self against thy true and sincere worship.</p>
               <p>And let thy name O God be worshipped in the beauty of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, let the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the wicked
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:45356:142"/> come to an end, But guide, &amp; establish, and prosper thou the just; let thy fear; be in the hearts of all thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, of what degree, or quality soever, mind every one of us, That the fear of the Lord, that is the beginning, and the end, the Top, and perfection of true wisdom, therfore, that in our several Stations, and callings, we may walk with thee, in all integrity, and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:45356:143"/> and with one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in all Justice, and Charity, Christian Tenderness, and Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loving Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</p>
               <p>And receive O Lord, the glory due to thy name, for the great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences which thou hast given us, of thy All-sufficiency and good providence, That thou hast renued upon us, the light of this day, and these precious opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:45356:143"/> of waiting upon thee, O make us sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of this wonderful long-suffering of thine, that the doors of thy house are not yet shut upon us, and those things are not hidden from our eyes, under which we have been so long unprofitable. Now, as it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed thee, to bring us together at this time, so bless thou, and san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie this our meeting, that it may not be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:45356:144"/> in vain, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny soul that is here before thee; We are now come to draw water out of the wells of salvation, O let us not return empty, let us not depart from thy presēce, without some Testimony of thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence; O that we might this day find some light added to our Judgements, some life and quickening to our cold, dead Affections, some Reformation to
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:45356:144"/> our lives, That these our services may be to the glory of thy great name, to the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge and comfort of our consciences, to the furtherance of our great account, in the day of our Lord Jesus; And be ye lifted up, O ye everlasting doors of our hearts, that the King of Glory may come in, that he may come in at this time, and take possession of us, and dwell, and
<pb n="274" facs="tcp:45356:145"/> reign in us for ever. Even so O Lord, for the sake of the Son of thy love, in whom on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we trust to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, and in whose name, and words, we further call upon thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="275" facs="tcp:45356:145"/>
               <head>Mr. <hi>SPARKE</hi> his Prayer before Sermon.</head>
               <p>LEt the Words of my Mouth and the Meditations of all our hearts be now and ever acceptable in thy sight, Oh Lord my Strength and my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</p>
               <p>O Most glorious and eternal God, before whom all the World doth tremble, before whom the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:45356:146"/> are impure, and the very Cherubims cover their faces, such is thine infinite per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, Be graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous notwithstanding through thy Christ &amp; our Jesus unto us sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wretches, and wretched sinners, who here presumptuously prostrate our Souls &amp; bodies before thy sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred presence, fully renouncing our own, and wholly relying on thy sons merits.</p>
               <pb n="277" facs="tcp:45356:146"/>
               <p>For we confesse oh Lord, we confess, that the very best of us are nothing else but Sons and Daughters of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, the pollution of whose nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the sole inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of our first Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, is so unsavory in thy nostrils, that had our Mothers womb been our untimely Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, it could not have exempted us from holding up a guilty hand at the bar
<pb n="278" facs="tcp:45356:147"/> of thy justice; what then shall become of us O Lord, who to this original corruption, have for so many years daily, hourly added actual transgression! and if one sin in <hi>Adam</hi> were enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn a whole world, Lord what are a world of sins to condem one poor soul! a world of actual sins; Sins of all Magnitudes, aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and degrees, sins of weakness against
<pb n="279" facs="tcp:45356:147"/> thee O God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who art power; sins of ignorance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thee O God the Son, who art wisdom; and sins of malice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thee O God the Holy Ghost, that art love.</p>
               <p>So that if we consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what we are, and what we do here, we may well hold up our hands, but hang down our heads abased at our own wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</p>
               <pb n="280" facs="tcp:45356:148"/>
               <p>For we have given up all the Faculties of our Souls, and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of our bodies, weapons of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness, and instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of sin; our ears have been often stopt at the voyce of thy true charmers; our throats an open Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher of the good name, and reputation of our neighbour; the poyson of Asps too oft under our lips; our eyes that should
<pb n="281" facs="tcp:45356:148"/> be the lights of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, dark and wicked; our hands impure, and dried up from all well doing; our feet swift to shed blood of our own souls and others; our hearts treasury of all, only evill, and that continually! yet are we but clay, and thou O Lord that Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that canst turn us into nothing, because we are thy creatures; yea, that mightest cast us into hell for ever,
<pb n="282" facs="tcp:45356:149"/> because we are thy sinful creatures, were not thy mercies over all thy works!</p>
               <p>But one deep calls upon another, our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable, sins on thine immeasurable mercies; look not on us O Lord, look not on us as in our selves mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable objects of thy wrath &amp; fury, behold us not as we are putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied branches, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold us in the sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of that root of
<pb n="283" facs="tcp:45356:149"/>
                  <hi>Iesse.</hi> Spare us good Lord, spare us for thy Son, who sparedst not thy Son for us, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not O Lord, remember not what we have so often done against thy Christ, but consider O Lord, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider what our Jesus hath once for all done for us.</p>
               <p>And not for us alone, but for thy whole Church militant how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever dispersed or despised through a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="284" facs="tcp:45356:150"/> world. Be as thou hast promised a wall of fire about her, and set a continual light in the midst thereof. O Lord shine to them that sit in darkness, and in the shadow of death, reveal thy Son, and his saving Gospel to those <hi>Asiaticks, Africans,</hi> and <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricans</hi> that never heard of a crucified Jesus. Add the fulness of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to the recolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that
<pb n="285" facs="tcp:45356:150"/> there may at length be one sheepfold under that one good and great Shepherd Jesus Christ.</p>
               <p>For whose sake look with a particular Eye of Mercy upon the bleeding and dying face of thy Church in these Nations; O Lord compose our unhappy differences, make up these sad breaches, which our sins have made so wide, that nothing but thine al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
<pb n="286" facs="tcp:45356:151"/> hand can close them: O Lord stench the bloody issue where it is; and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it elsewhere by a gracious mercy, by a timely melting the hearts of these obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Nations one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another in bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly compassion, one towards another in their lawful subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <p>But especially by melting all of us to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee our God
<pb n="287" facs="tcp:45356:151"/> offended, in an unfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned humiliation. And that in blessing thou maist bless, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee O Lord, to continue those two bright Beams of thy power and wisdom, that is the lawful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistracy and Ministry still among us; in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sense, quench not O Lord, quench not utterly the light of <hi>Israel;</hi> and to that end blesse I pray thee all those whom thy holy
<pb n="288" facs="tcp:45356:152"/> word commandeth us to pray for, <hi>viz.</hi> all Kings, Princes, and Governours, especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ours; and for the happier supply of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> Chair, and <hi>Aarons</hi> Ephod, bless those Twins of knowledge, the two Famous Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series of learning, <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Oxford;</hi> keep those Mothers from dry Brests, and from miscarrying wombs, purge those Fountains from Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie
<pb n="289" facs="tcp:45356:152"/> and Schism; make them again like <hi>Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> from whence may ever come fit Cedars to build up thy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               <p>And thou who art a God not only of the Mountains, but also of the Valleys, suffer that precious ointment of thy Heavenly benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction not alone to wet the head of this our Land, but likewise to distil upon the beard and skirts the Nobility
<pb n="290" facs="tcp:45356:153"/> therof Gentry &amp; comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty; bless all thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from the Cedar to the Hysop, from the swaier of the Scepter to the drawer of Water, from the highest Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite to the lowest Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonite. And whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther now shall the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stressed look for help, but from the Hills? send them help O Lord from thy holy Hill; comfort with thy Staff all those whom thou hast afflicted
<pb n="291" facs="tcp:45356:153"/> with thy rod; and let no bodily diseased <hi>Job,</hi> or Soul-sick <hi>Eliah</hi> desparingly sigh out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny longer, is there no Balme in <hi>Gilead?</hi> is there no Physician there? But hear thou O Lord in Heaven, and have mercy; break not these bruised Reeds, but bind up the broken hearted; and for those whom thou hast stretched up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their beds of lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishment, make thou
<pb n="292" facs="tcp:45356:154"/> their beds in all their sickness; draw near unto them according to their several neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities; be thou the good Physician to their bodies, and say to them as sometimes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> I will yet add unto your dayes; however be the good <hi>Samaritan</hi> to their Souls, &amp; as to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> say to them, thou art their salvation. Be further entreated for this sinfull Land and
<pb n="293" facs="tcp:45356:154"/> Nation! let the further cup of blood passe from it, yet not our wills but thy will be done: if the measure of our sins challenge the further vials of thy wrath, we beseech thee with unfeigned hearts give a happy victory to thy truth, and by thy mighty power preserve all those that are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to dy; In the mean time oh Lord give us and all other afflicted
<pb n="294" facs="tcp:45356:155"/> places and persons pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and Christian resolution, cheerfully to go through whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thy fatherly cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stising hand shall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict upon us; and in thy good time which is the best, Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass us all about with songs of deliverance.</p>
               <p>Let not my Lord be angry and I will speak unto thee yet but this once, craving a bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing on thine own or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance; O Lord be
<pb n="295" facs="tcp:45356:155"/> present among us who are here present in thy Sanctuary, and say of this congregation as <hi>Isaac</hi> of <hi>Jacob,</hi> I have blest it, and it shall be blessed.</p>
               <p>Bless me O Lord the most unworthy of all the Sons of <hi>Aaron;</hi> and because I am a Man of uncircumcised lips, O Lord be thou with my mouth and with my heart also as with thy servant <hi>Moses,</hi> and teach me what to say.
<pb n="296" facs="tcp:45356:156"/> Lastly with <hi>Davids</hi> Key, open and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the hearts of these thy people, that they like good Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, hearing thy word attentively, may like good Stewards use the same carefully, and in their lives like good ground may bring forth fruits effectually, so shall thy name be glorified, their selves here somewhat farther edified, all our Souls finally saved at the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="297" facs="tcp:45356:156"/> appearing of thine only Son, our only Saviour Jesus Christ, in whose sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred name, merit and Sole Mediation, we beg off thy judgments and intreat thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, saying as he hath taught us, &amp; comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="298" facs="tcp:45356:157"/>
               <head>The Prayer of <hi>John Marston B. D.</hi> before his Sermon.</head>
               <p>GReat and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God, whose presence (though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visible) fils all places, whose providence is the admiration of all men, and whose pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is the scourge of the damned.</p>
               <p>Thy power (O Lord)
<pb n="299" facs="tcp:45356:157"/> made the World, and thy displeasure can blast the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, till it dis-subsist and become nothing.</p>
               <p>Thy power amaseth us, and because we merit, therefore we fear, thy Justice; and our own horrors drink up our spirits, whilst our Consciences both represent, and reprove our sins.</p>
               <p>We have sinned (O Lord) and our sins have multiplied, and
<pb n="300" facs="tcp:45356:158"/> outvied the haires of our head, and are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come no less than infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite both in their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and our inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Age it self, which sheds our hairs and makes them few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, multiplies our sins, and makes them more. Every Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment accuseth us; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Period of time reproacheth us. Our Infancie was wrapt up in Ignorance. Our ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per yeers gave us a
<pb n="301" facs="tcp:45356:158"/> dangerous knowledg, and by greater study and contrivance, made us wiser only to transgress: And Age it self, which abates the possibilities of some sins, hath so return'd our contemplations uppon them, that we have sinned over all those sins, by memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and delight.</p>
               <p>The sands (by the Sea-shore) rebuke us, for that our sins have larger bounds than
<pb n="302" facs="tcp:45356:159"/> they; Hell is full of the punishment, and horror of our sins; The Earth is defiled with the guilt, and Heaven offended with the clamor of our sins: But the Sea swells and hides the Sands, and with a waterie Robe covers their slime; but our sins (O Lord) are naked still, and (to thine eye) betray our shame.</p>
               <p>But, Lord, thou art infinite in mercie, and canst
<pb n="303" facs="tcp:45356:159"/> save more than we can sin: And though death only can conclude our sins, (for in that very Justice there was a mercie, &amp; the very pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment of sin became so much the Remedy, that after death we can never offend thee more) yet (Dearest God) thou canst (in this life) give us relief of Soul, and (by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveness) cancel our crimes, till thy pardon make them none.</p>
               <pb n="304" facs="tcp:45356:160"/>
               <p>The stretcht-out Arms of our dearest Saviour, on the Cross, Can encompass the largest extention of our sins; And his pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion affords an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing-red Sea, to cover and confound our sins, that they may not become our confusion.</p>
               <p>Springs of mercy flowed from his sacred head, when he was crowned with thorns; Because we advanc'd
<pb n="305" facs="tcp:45356:160"/> our heads in high looks, and (with a stiff neck) oppos'd thy will; he bowed his bleeding head on the Cross.</p>
               <p>Rivers of mercy flowd from his hands, to cleanse the oppressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ours.</p>
               <p>From his Feet (fast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened and unmoved) is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued a Current of bloud, because ours have been so swift to shed it: And lest we should want abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant
<pb n="306" facs="tcp:45356:161"/> supplies of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, the Floudgates stand open at his side, that so whilst Mercy, and Mysterie, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and Soul-sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, flow out all together, our Lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie may want no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, nor we (in our languishings) want support: Oh then let his bloud be our Bath, Purge us with Hysop and we shall be clean, wash us, and we shall be whiter than Snow:
<pb n="307" facs="tcp:45356:161"/> And to capacitate us for these mercies, Let deepest sorrow wound our Souls; Oh let it grieve our spirits, that we have lived so long the grief of thine, and let us grieve again that we can grieve no more: Make our Souls to ascend in humblest supplications, and let our Saviours Interces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion procure thine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of them (though our Incense ascend from unhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="308" facs="tcp:45356:162"/> Altars) And give us such a Faith as may take possession of all we pray for: And lest our own trust should deceive us, when we have sayd Amen to our prayers, do thou say Amen to our Amen, that so an establishment of bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings may be the Crown of our Souls.</p>
               <p>And because after the House is swept and garnished more Devils may enter in it, and
<pb n="309" facs="tcp:45356:162"/> make our later end worse than our begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; Give us Grace to watch against the re-assaults of old Sins, and to oppose the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments of new Sins; that execution may be the life of our resolves, and triumph the end of our warfare, whilst we work out our salvation with fear and trembling.</p>
               <p>Blessed Lord, with us we pray thee blesse thy catholick Church,
<pb n="310" facs="tcp:45356:163"/> preserve it from the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatries of those who call themselves Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques, and from the Heresies of those, who are become their own Idols, by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipping their own I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations.</p>
               <p>Advance, we pray thee, the Truth, and purity of Religion in this Nation, and to that end, let thy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit guide our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and us under his Government, that we
<pb n="311" facs="tcp:45356:163"/> may all lead a Godly and quiet life, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voring to keep the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Spirit in the bond of peace.</p>
               <p>Water, we beseech thee, the two Nurse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Religion and Learning, <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and in <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> continue thy old Favours to <hi>Magdalen</hi> College, that it may still flourish in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities and holiness of those it shall send out to serve at thine Altar.</p>
               <pb n="312" facs="tcp:45356:164"/>
               <p>Let the Magistrates of this Natiō know whose Sword they bear, and give them thy Grace, that they may execute Justice, and maintain Truth</p>
               <p>Let thy word be magnified by the Life and Doctrine of those whom are ordained to preach it, and let the People (having no mans person in Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration) receive thy word for it self, with that humility and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence,
<pb n="313" facs="tcp:45356:164"/> which befits the Oracles of God. Let the sick Man find thee a Physician, and let all that are afflicted find thee a Consolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Let not the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of life perplex, nor the horrors of death affright us, but both in life and death let our submissions testifie, that thy will is our Law: And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midst the very Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonies of death, suffer not our Faith to fail,
<pb n="314" facs="tcp:45356:165"/> nor our Hope of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to deceive us, nor our Charity to die be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, but let our very enemies be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for our prayers, for his sake who pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for his enemies, and whilst we were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies dyed for us.</p>
               <p>Oh let us live the life of the righteous, that we may dy the death of the righteous, that so thy servants may depart in peace, and then receive the
<pb n="315" facs="tcp:45356:165"/> end of their Hope, even the salvation of our Souls, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ our Lord, in obedience to whom, we conclude the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections of our own prayers, with that, which he hath appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, sanctified, and Commanded, saying when ye pray, Say <hi>Our Father which art in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="316" facs="tcp:45356:166"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Richard Ball <hi>his Prayer before Sermon.</hi> Let us call upon the name of the Lord.</head>
               <p>O Lord our God, we acknowledge and confesse that we are less than the least of all thy mercies, we are unworthy of the least crum that falls
<pb n="317" facs="tcp:45356:166"/> from the table of thy ordinary providence, we are unworthy of those common favors which thou vouchsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est to the Birds of the air, and to the Lillies of the field, to be clothed, and to be fed; how, much more, O Lord, unworthy are we to appear in thy presence, to call upon thy great and glorious name with any confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that thou wilt hear our prayers and
<pb n="318" facs="tcp:45356:167"/> grant our requests? and as we are unworthy, so we are altogether unable to perform any holy duty that may be pleasing and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in thy sight: but we come unto thee in the name of thy dear Son who is most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, in whose name thou hast promised to grant unto us whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we shall ask; we come unto thee in his name, O Lord, at this time, for the assistance
<pb n="319" facs="tcp:45356:167"/> of thy holy and of thy blessed <hi>Spirit,</hi> who is able to supply all our weakness and all our insufficiency; there is not any thing, O Lord, that hath betrayed us the Children of men to all this unworthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and all this weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, but only our sins; we do desire O Lord, in the sincerity of our hearts, to spread our sins before thee at this time by an humble &amp; by a sincere Cōfessiō of
<pb n="320" facs="tcp:45356:168"/> them; we acknowledg, O Lord, to thy glory, and our own shame, that thou madest us upright, but we have sought out many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, we have lost that glorious Image of thine wherein at first we were created, and we have contracted many vicious habits and dispositions wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are prone to evil, and only evil, and that continually; we have lived with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="321" facs="tcp:45356:168"/> thee in the World, and thou hast not been in all our thoughts; &amp; not only without thee, but contrary unto thee; we have been not only Strangers, but enemies, making all the faculties of our Souls, and members of our Bodies, as so many instruments and weapons of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness, our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standings have been full of darkness and blindness, our Wills
<pb n="322" facs="tcp:45356:169"/> of crookedness and perversness, our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of disorder and tumult; our eies have been full of wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonness, our tongues have been trumpeters of folly, our hands have been full of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and oppression, and our feet have been swift to shed blood; we have, O Lord, been universally contrary unto thee; we have loved that which thou hatest, and
<pb n="323" facs="tcp:45356:169"/> we have hated that which thou lovest; we have sinned against thee with a high hand, against thy patience &amp; long-suffering, against the motions of thy Spirit, against the Checks of our Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, against the call of thy Ministers those sweet embassadors of thy peace, against ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mercies to allure us, and against many judgements both nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal and personal
<pb n="324" facs="tcp:45356:170"/> which should have been as so many Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sengers to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd us to come in: but, O Lord our God, we have hardened our hearts against thy fear, we have sinned against thee not only in the days of ignorance when thou winkedst at it, but after illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, after many vowes and promises of better obedience; we have been unfaithfull
<pb n="325" facs="tcp:45356:170"/> and unsteadfast before thee, all our r ghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness hath been as a morning dew and as a cloud that vanisheth away, like the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Ephraim</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing harnessed and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying bowes, we have turned our selves back in the day of battel, being munited and fortified in some measure with the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of thy holy Spirit, and many a heavenly purpose and resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="326" facs="tcp:45356:171"/> we have not so couragiously resisted the temptations of Satan, and of this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evil World, and the corruptions of our own hearts, as we ought to have done, but we have turned our selves back in the day of that Spiritual battail, and we have been foyled and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered again and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; and we confess O Lord farther against our selves, that we
<pb n="327" facs="tcp:45356:171"/> have as it were sealed up all these our sins in a bag by hardness of heart, by impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of life, and by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of security. Father, we have sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against thee, what shall we do unto thee O thou the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>server of men? O Lord thou knowest that it is not in man to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his own waies, O when Lord Jesus, when shall it once be? O thou that by thy al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
<pb n="328" facs="tcp:45356:172"/> power didst bring water out of a rock, we beseech thee smite the stony Rocks of our hearts, and make the water of a true &amp; of an unfeigned Repentance to gush forth; give us that godly sorrow that may work repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance never to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of; help us, O Lord, to carry all our sins even with sorrow to our graves, and yet, O Lord, not with the sorrow of anxiety or
<pb n="329" facs="tcp:45356:172"/> desperation, but with the sorrow of contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the sorrow of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, the sorrow of a sound and of an unfeigned repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Forgive, O Lord, forgive what ever is past for Jesus sake the Son of thy love in whom thou art well pleased; there's no other name given under heaven by which we can be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, there is no orher fountain set open for
<pb n="330" facs="tcp:45356:173"/>
                  <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jerusalem</hi> to wash in for sin and for uncleanness; we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beseech thee to bath and wash our polluted Souls in that most precious foūtain, wash us, O Lord from the guilt of our sins, wash us from the stains and pollutions of our sins, wash us from the power and dominion of our sins; look not O Lord upon what we have done, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what thy Son
<pb n="331" facs="tcp:45356:173"/> Christ Jesus hath both done and sufferd, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of his obedience for our disobedience, and by his Stripes let our sinfull Souls be healed; he hath ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fild that law which we have so often and so fearfully broken, he hath suffered that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment which we have so often and so justly deserved, thy Justice is compleatly satisfyed in thy Son; we humbly pray thee
<pb n="332" facs="tcp:45356:174"/> to magnifie thy mercy in the pardoning and in the forgiving of us miserable sinners; seal unto us, O Lord, the pardon of all that is past by the testimony of thy holy and of thy blessed Spirit; that as there is peace made in heaven for us, so there may be peace in our Consciences within us; plant in our hearts the fear of thy holy name for the time to come, that we may
<pb n="333" facs="tcp:45356:174"/> walk before thee more exactly, more circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectly &amp; wisely, redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the time because the dayes are evil. Give us power and strength against our corruptions, let not sin Reign in our mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal bodies, that we should fulfil it in the lusts thereof; bruise Satan under our feet shortly, according to thy sweet and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promise; help us especially to eschew
<pb n="334" facs="tcp:45356:175"/> our own wickedness, that sin which by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or custom, or constitution, or temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, we have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore been most prone and subject un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, because by that we have most dishonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thy Majesty, and grieved thy Spirit, and wounded our own Consciences; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause O Lord there is no man liveth and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, we humbly pray thee to keep thy
<pb n="335" facs="tcp:45356:175"/> poor Servants from presūptuous sins, that they may never get the dominion over us; when we sin of infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, O let our hearts smite us speedily; ever more keep us from im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency, deadnesse of heart, presumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wickedness, and a down-falling into sin; vouchsafe unto every one of us all those gifts and graces, which thou knowest to be needful, and requisite
<pb n="336" facs="tcp:45356:176"/> for us in all estate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and conditions of life, where unto thou shalt be pleased to call us, &amp; wherein thou shalt be pleased to exercise us; in adversity, O Lord, give us patience, in prosperity thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness, and in both humility, and meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and lowliness of mind; increase our Faith, confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m our hope, inflame our cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Crown all thy graces in us with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>severance
<pb n="337" facs="tcp:45356:176"/> to the end; grant, O Lord, that we may so run, that wee may obtain, and that the Gates of Hell may never be able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail against us; let nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prosperity, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity, life, or death, things present, or things to come, be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver able to separate us from the love of thee in Christ Jesus our Lord; in whose holy name, we continue our requests, for thy
<pb n="338" facs="tcp:45356:177"/> whole Church where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever dispersed, or howsoever distressed, upon the face of the whole earth, adde un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Church daily those that shall be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, bring home thine antient people, the Jews, gather together the fulnesse of the Gentiles, finish these dayes of sin, and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and then come Lord JESUS, come quickly. Have pitty upon these sinful Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="339" facs="tcp:45356:177"/> of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move thy heavy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are upon us, withhold those that hang over us, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give our crying sins, compose our sad diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, create peace; bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Jesus, with a word of thy mouth, thou didst still the winds, and the waves when they Arose, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servedst thy Disciples, we humbly beseech thee, to extend thy
<pb n="340" facs="tcp:45356:178"/> power, and goodness, and lay all storms, and Tempests, both in Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; send us a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious tranquillity, a blessed peace, as may be most for thy glory, for the refreshment of thy people, that do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend and wait upon thee, and for the dissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating and scattering of all those that do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in War. O raise up many to stand in the gap like <hi>Aaron,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="341" facs="tcp:45356:178"/> the living and the dead, to turn thy wrathful indignation from us; hear the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and the Sighes, and the tears of those that mourn in secret, for all the abominations that have been committed in the midst of us, and above all hear the voyce of the blood of thy Son Christ Jesus, that speaketh better things than the blood of <hi>Abel.</hi> And thou that art the God of all
<pb n="342" facs="tcp:45356:179"/> pitty, and all compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, have pitty upon all those that suffer for the Testimony of a good Conscience, give them health, and strength, and patience, a sanctified use, and a joyfull deliverance; prepare us for Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and alterations; give us a contented mind in all estates, that we may sing with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> our heart is fixed, O God, our heart is fixed, whom have we
<pb n="343" facs="tcp:45356:179"/> in Heaven but thee? and there is none up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, that we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire in comparison of thee, That the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries of the world may never corrupt us, nor the frowns of it terrifie us, but that we may in the midst of all storms and tempests of persecution, with a quiet mind and a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Conscience look up to heaven, and with the eie of faith behold that glorious
<pb n="344" facs="tcp:45356:180"/> vision, which thy faithfull Martyr Saint <hi>Stephen</hi> did with the eye of his body, even heaven opened, and Jesus standing at the right hand in glory, both to strengthen us in all Spiritual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats and agonies, and to Crown us after them. And thou that art the Physician both of Body and Soul, have mercy upon all those that are visited with thy hand of sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
<pb n="345" facs="tcp:45356:180"/> and especially on those thy servants who desire the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of our Prayers at this time; Those who draw neer the time of travail, Lord shew thy powet in their weakness, and mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defend them; make them joyful Mothers of those children. Those that are tossed upon the Seas, who are gone forth, or coming home, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect and defend them
<pb n="346" facs="tcp:45356:181"/> from Rocks, &amp; Sands from Storms, and Tempests, from Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, and Robbers, and bring them in safety to the Haven where they would be, and give them good success. As for those who are tossed upon the Bed of pain, or sickness, Lord give them ease, Lord give them help; lay no more upon them, than thou wilt inable them to bear; bless all means
<pb n="347" facs="tcp:45356:181"/> that shall be used for their recovery, and let not their sickness be to death if it be thy blessed will: However thou dealest with their bodies, be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and propitious to their Souls, though the outward man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, yet let the inward man be renewed day by day: and when their bodies shall go the way of all the earth, grant that their Souls may go the way
<pb n="348" facs="tcp:45356:182"/> of thy Saints and of thy Servants. And we beseech thee, gratious God, to sanctifie all spectacles of frailty, and Mortality, to us that are in health and strength, help us to wait all the dayes of our appointed time until our change shall come, make us all wise Virgins that we may get oyl into our lamps, not only the lamps of profession, but the oyl of sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;
<pb n="349" facs="tcp:45356:182"/> that we may be allwayes ready to go in with thee the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom of our Souls when soever it shall please thee to come unto us, either by thy general or by thy par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular visitation. And seing, O Lord, we have begun to speak unto thee, our selvs being but dust and ashes, O let not our Lord be angry, and we will speak but this once more for a blessing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="350" facs="tcp:45356:183"/> thy own ordināce, bless me, O Lord, who am to speak, open thou my lips and my mouth shall shew forth thy praise, give me strength of body and mind, a heart studious of thy Glory, and the good of thy people commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to my charge, make me faithfull as in thy presence, that I may never for fear, or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, conceal and hide that sense of scripture
<pb n="351" facs="tcp:45356:183"/> from thy people, which was intruded by thy blessed Spirit, and insteed thereof, fasten upon it my own inventions, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations, which is the highest sacrilege that can be committed in this World, and that which in all times hath betrayed thine own people to many, not only foolish, but dangerous errors; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare, O Lord, the hearts of this people, for the
<pb n="352" facs="tcp:45356:184"/> hearing and receiving of thy holy word, that they may receive it with meekness and due reverence, open their hearts as thou didst the heart of <hi>Lyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,</hi> enlighten those that are ignorant, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce those that go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stray, comfort those that are afflicted, raise up those that fall, strengthen those that are weak, confirm and establish those that are strong, bring us all
<pb n="353" facs="tcp:45356:184"/> nearer and nearer to thy majesty. These mercies, O thou God of mercy, we beg of thee, in the name, and for the merits, and in the words of thy Christ &amp; our Jesus, saying as he hath taught us, <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="354" facs="tcp:45356:185"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Or Thus</hi> Let us call upon the name of the Lord</head>
               <p>Look down from heaven, O Lord, upon us, with the eyes of thy mercy, in a free pardon and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveness of all our sins, for number many, and for nature heinous: give unto us, O Lord, a true sight of them, a
<pb n="355" facs="tcp:45356:185"/> serious tepentance for them, and a constant purpose and resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on never to return un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. And for the dayes that we have yet to live, grant that we may pass the time of our sojourning here in fear, remembring that we are pilgrims and strangers as all our Fathers were, and that we have no abiding City; teach us to live as those that must dy, and after death come
<pb n="356" facs="tcp:45356:186"/> to Judgement; guide us here, O Lord, by thy counsel, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards receive us into thy glory—Bless the holy Catholic Church, defend her and streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then her, O God, that with courage and vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory she may fight thy battels, and allwayes maintain that enmity which thou hast set betwixt the seed of the woman, and the seed of the Serpent. Stil continue to spread
<pb n="357" facs="tcp:45356:186"/> thy wings of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and protection over the Churches of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> let not the wilde Boar of the field by supersttion and idolatry lay them waste, neither suffer those little Foxes by factions and schisms to root them up: remove most gratious God, thy heavy judgements that are upon us, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold those that hang over us, <hi>&amp;c</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="358" facs="tcp:45356:187"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>As it followes in the former Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="359" facs="tcp:45356:187"/>
               <head>Mr. <hi>Ball</hi> his Prayer after Sermon.</head>
               <p>HOly, Holy, Holy, Lord God of Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boath, Heaven and Earth are full of the Majesty of thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, it is the imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Saints &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels to adore thee, and to worship thee, and
<pb n="360" facs="tcp:45356:188"/> to fall down before thee; The Cherubins they cover their faces, as being unworthy to look up unto thee, and they cover their feet, as being unworthy that thou shouldest look down upon them; It is the desire of thy Saints and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants here on Earth, that thy will may be done on Earth, as it is in Heaven; We desire to adore thee, and to worship thee, in the
<pb n="361" facs="tcp:45356:188"/> contemplation of thy great glory. Thou art a God who art infinite in power, and infinite in purity; Thou art the great Creator of Heaven and Earth; Thou art the wise Disposer, &amp; Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of all things; Thou dwellest in the Light that is inaccessible; It is little O Lord, that we know of thee, while we are here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; We see all things here darkly, and as in
<pb n="362" facs="tcp:45356:189"/> a glasse; But we desire to see and know so much, that we may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore thee, and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence thee, and fear before thee; Enlarge our hearts with thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse, and fill our mouths with praises, for all thy goodnesse, &amp; for all thy Mercies, that thou hast commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to us thy poor Creatures; We blesse thee for creating us af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thine own Image, for redeeming us
<pb n="363" facs="tcp:45356:189"/> when we had lost it; a favour which thou deniedst to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, when they sinned against thee; Above all, we blesse thee for thy dear Son, the Sun of thy Love, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est gift which ever thou didst give to the Sons of Men. We bless thee for his Incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for his holy Life, &amp; patient Death, for his glorious Resurrection and Ascension, and for the comming of the
<pb n="364" facs="tcp:45356:190"/> Holy Ghost. We bless thee for all temporal favours, from thee cometh every good, as well as every perfect gift; We blesse thee for our Health, whilest others are upon their Beds of Sicknesse; We blesse thee for our lives, while others are gone into their graves, the Land where all things are forgotten; We bless thee for our plenty, while others are in scarcity &amp; famin,
<pb n="365" facs="tcp:45356:190"/> We blesse thee for our Peace, whilst others are in War; We bless thee for our Liberty, while others are in Prison; Especially O Lord, we blesse thee for these spiritual Liberties, of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into thy House, of calling upon thy Name, of hearing, and speaking thy most ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Word, the things that do concern our everlasting Peace; Oh never suffer them to
<pb n="366" facs="tcp:45356:191"/> be hid from our Eyes, in this the day of our visitation; We humbly pray thee to pardon &amp; pas by all weaknesses and frailties, that have been this day, either in the Speaker, or in the Hearers, take away from us the iniquity, of our holy things; Let not thy blessings be upon us according to any Excellency or Worth that is in our Performances, nothing belongs to us, but
<pb n="367" facs="tcp:45356:191"/> Shame and Confusion of face, but let thy blessings be upon us, according to thy rich and free Mercy; <hi>Paul</hi> may plant, and <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo</hi> may water, but thou art the God that givest the encrease; thou art the God that teachest us to profit, we look up unto thee for a Blessing, and we beseech thee to grant, that the Words which we have heard this day with our outward
<pb n="368" facs="tcp:45356:192"/> Ears, may through thy grace, be so grafted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in our Hearts, that they may bring forth in us the fruit of good living, to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and praise of thy Name, through Jesus Christ our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:45356:192"/>
            <head>The names of those whose Payers you have in this Manuel.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Reeve</hi> Dean of <hi>Chichester</hi> his Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er before Sermon. fo. <hi>1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Gillingham's</hi> Prayer before Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. fo. <hi>38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Jeremy Taylor</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:45356:193"/> his Prayer before Sermon. fo. <hi>54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Prayer after Sermon. fo. <hi>77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Hewet</hi> his Prayer before Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. fo. <hi>83</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Meditations and Prayers for the sick, by Dr. <hi>Wild.</hi> fo. <hi>124</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Thanksgiving for ease in sickness or Recovery out of it, by
<pb facs="tcp:45356:193"/> Dr. <hi>Wild.</hi> fo. <hi>141</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Griffith</hi> his Prayer before Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. fo. <hi>149</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> his Prayer before Sermon. fo. <hi>156</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Goddard,</hi> late Minister at Saint <hi>Gregories,</hi> his Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er before Sermon. fo. <hi>172</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Nr. <hi>Nathan Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> his Prayer before
<pb facs="tcp:45356:194"/> Sermon. fo. <hi>210</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Machinest</hi> his Prayer before Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. fo. <hi>236</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Hall</hi> at Saint <hi>Botolphs</hi> Alders<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate his Prayer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sermon. fo. <hi>249</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Sparks</hi> his Prayer before Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. fo. <hi>275</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>John Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ston.</hi> B. D. his Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb facs="tcp:45356:194"/> before Serman fo. <hi>298</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Richard Ball</hi> his Prayer before Sermon. fo. <hi>316</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Prayer after Sermon. fo. <hi>359</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb facs="tcp:45356:195"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45356:195"/>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A privat Prayer to be said before thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Lords Supper.</head>
               <byline>
                  <hi>By</hi> John Reading <hi>late Minister of</hi> Dover.</byline>
               <p>MOst gracious Lord God, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercy &amp; truth, who dwelling in that light which none can
<pb facs="tcp:45356:196"/> attain unto, yet vouchsafest to prepare the hearts of thy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants here on earth to help their infirmities, and to hear their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: prepare my heart, teach me to pray, encline thine ear unto me, and have mercy upon me. O Lord thou art a just and a severe Iudge, how shall I then (vile &amp; unwor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy wretch) appear this d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y before thee in the Courts
<pb facs="tcp:45356:196"/> of thy house? I came into this world a childe of wrath and disobedience, naked and destitute of all goodness: but O Lord my Redeemer, thou hast bestowed the seal of thy righteousnesse upon me in my Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism, thou hast cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thy Gospel, thou hast given me the inward seal and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest of my Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the Spirit of
<pb facs="tcp:45356:197"/> Regeneration: Lord establish the thing thou hast freely wrought in me. And as thou hast this day invited me to thy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the body and blood of thy Son <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> so Lord bestow the wedding garment on me, that I may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before thee cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in the righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of thy Son <hi>Jesus,</hi> whom thou madest an offering for sin, that
<pb facs="tcp:45356:197"/> in him we might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come righteous before thee. Lord, what is man that thou so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardest him? and who among the Sons of men hath more cause to praise thy mercies than wretched I? Thy mercy hath long spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me, thou hast ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me out of the power of darknesse, and Kingdome of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan; thou hast given me the glorious free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the children
<pb facs="tcp:45356:198"/> of light: What shall I render the Lord for all his benefits towards me? I will call upon the name of the Lord, I will declare his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, I will take the Cup of Salvation, and pay my vowes. All is too little which I have to give thee: O Lord thou hast in my crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion given me my self; in my Redemption thou hast restored me to my self; therefore now accept again
<pb facs="tcp:45356:198"/> thine own gift; Lord let me be wholly thine. And being now to appear before thee with a Sacrifice of praise, Lord I pray thee for <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> his sake, prepare the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of my heart, purge me with Hysop that I may be clean.</p>
               <p>Create a clean heart within me, and renew a right spirit: Sprinkle the door of my Soul with the blood of the Lamb of God, which
<pb facs="tcp:45356:199"/> taketh away the sins of the World, that the destroyer may not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Send down thy grace and holy Spirit into my heart, with that heavenly fire of love to thee, and true charity to all men, which may assure me of thy acceptance of me. Cleanse out of me all the old leven of sin and maliciousness. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen my understāding, increase my faith, that I may see and know
<pb facs="tcp:45356:199"/> the assurance of my sins remission in these seals of eternal life, which by thy mercy I am to receive. Thou hast taught me, O Lord, that my blessed Saviour in the night that he was betrayed, made this his holy Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament, wherein as he took flesh &amp; blood of us, that he might dy for us, so he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed his body &amp; blood to us, that we might live in him; and
<pb facs="tcp:45356:200"/> left this Sacrament as a faithfull pledge of his love, to remember us of his dying for us till he come again. O Lord I know thou art the life and truth, and wouldest not have left thy Church any ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectless pledge of their salvation. Lord <hi>Jesus</hi> therefore be present with my spirit, work powerfully on thine own ordinance, that it may indeed seal up my Salvation in my
<pb facs="tcp:45356:200"/> Soul with that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant assurance, that the gates of Hell may never prevail against it: that no terrour of Conscience, nor any delusions of Satan may be able to overthrow it; But that I may with a lively Faith lay hold on all the merits of Jesus Christ, that I may find therein an inward peace in confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of my sins for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveness, recōciliation with my God, sound
<pb facs="tcp:45356:201"/> joy in the Holy Ghost my Comforter, sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied will and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, purity of life, and holy obedience, which hath the testimony of a good conscience; to be a sweet comfort in life and death: assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring me that I have fought a good fight, and kept the faith, and therefore shall enjoy that crown of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness, which the Lord the righteous judge shall at that day
<pb facs="tcp:45356:201"/> give to all them that love his appearing. Grant this O Lord, and what ever else thou knowest to be needfull for me, for <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> his sake, who with thee O Father, and the holy Spirit, liveth and reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ever one God, world without end.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:45356:202"/>
               <head>A Private Prayer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter receiving the Lords Supper.</head>
               <byline>By Mr. <hi>Reading, &amp;c.</hi>
               </byline>
               <p>MOst gracious God, and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Father, who of thine own free love and good pleasure hast elected, created, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, reconciled, justified and preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved me, and hast also
<pb facs="tcp:45356:202"/> bestowed on me the peaceable use of thy holy Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: I humbly thank thee for all thy mercies which thou hast shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, as also for this present comfort which I have now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived at thy merciful hands. O Lord, accept this sacrifice of praise and thanksgiving through Iesus Christ: perfect the work which thou hast begun in me, make good thine own
<pb facs="tcp:45356:203"/> Ordinance unto my Soul, seal me up to the day of Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, kindle in me full assurance of my sins re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission and reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation with thee, lively sense of my union with Christ, and Christ his living in me, and guiding me so by his holy Spirit, that his life may appear in all my actions, words, and thoughts, and that I may henceforth no more live to sin, but
<pb facs="tcp:45356:203"/> being freed from the lawes thereof, may have my fruits unto holiness and salvation. Lord therefore make me every day more &amp; more able to do thy Will, and to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don mine own cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt desires: Let me feel in my Soul and Conscience the real benefit of thy Word and Sacraments, which thou hast promised to all those who truly seek thee, give me
<pb facs="tcp:45356:204"/> that longing desire of righteousness which is by thy Grace secured from despair, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served from vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and presumption: satisfie me with that measure of Grace, which thy wisdome knoweth sufficient for me: Lord make me know that I have not now received this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in vain, let me hereby be nourished unto eternal Life, and obtain a better strēgth
<pb facs="tcp:45356:204"/> to walk before thee, till I come to thy holy mountain, the land of the living: Give me a sound and lively faith, give me cheerfulness of heart in a spiritual tasting of the Tree of Life: My Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, give me a firm and comfortable peace of Conscience, with that joy of the holy Ghost, which may assure me that thy Kingdome is established in me: give me a zealous love of
<pb facs="tcp:45356:205"/> thy glory, ready obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to thy Law, fear to displease thee, and holy love to all my brethren, (which may give me boldness in the Day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) with that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameableness of life and conversation w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg>. may be to thy glory, and the good example of those with whom I live. Assist me with thy sanctifying Spirit, that I may perform all those vowes, which I
<pb facs="tcp:45356:205"/> have made to serve thee, &amp; that every day of my life may be to me as this Sabbath, an holy rest from sin: Lord prevent the subtilty of the Tempter, and let thy holy Spirit keep me body and Soul: Give me an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contempt of this present world, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections set on heaven, where my blessed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jesus Christ sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at thy right hand, who will in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb facs="tcp:45356:206"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:45356:206"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:45356:207"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:45356:207"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:45356:208"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:45356:208"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:45356:209"/> time appear in Judgement, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all his Saints unto him.</p>
               <p>These things, and whatsoever else thou knowest needfull for me, or any part of the whole Church Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant here on earth, I beg at thy gracious hands, who hast com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to ask, and promised to give. O Lord incline thine ear and hear: O Lord, give a Gracious Answer
<pb facs="tcp:45356:209"/> through Jesus Christ our Lord: To whom with thee O Father of mercy, and the holy Ghost the Comforter, be all honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in heaven and earth to all eternity, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="prayers">
            <pb facs="tcp:45356:210"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45356:210"/>
            <head>Litaniae breves pro diversis hominum statibus &amp; necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus Officio ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendae pro placito.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Exaudi nos precantes Domine Deus, Jesu Christi atque mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricordiarum Pater,</head>
               <p>PRo universá Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siâ, quam immobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem &amp; tranquillam, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam,
<pb facs="tcp:45356:211"/> &amp; in Partibus coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunatam, immunem a Schismate, haeresi &amp; Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegio custodias ad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>summationem saeculi: ut coelestem spem singula membra persequantur, &amp; ut donum Orationis, &amp; officium solenne sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candi jugiter operentur; &amp; per gratiam Christi &amp; Dei Patris salutem, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictionem, custodiam, &amp; pietatem nobis omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; singulis largire gratiosè.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:45356:211"/>
               <head>Exaudi nos precan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Domine De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Jesu Christi &amp; misericordia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Pater.</head>
               <p>Pro Regibus &amp; Duci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Populorum, maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè verò pro serenissimo nostre Rege, cui ut Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum principalem, Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Sapientiae, Pietatis &amp; Consilii largiaris, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militer rogamus; pro Eodem, &amp; pro omnibus Principibus, ut vivant in pace atque honore, ut eos
<pb facs="tcp:45356:212"/> timeant, &amp; ament po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli, &amp; illi Deum, ut sint Nutritii Ecclesiarum, Patres Orphanorum, &amp; Judices Viduarum, ut miseriis inopum, &amp; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitibus Oppressorum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doleaut, ne populum Dei ob rem nihili lacerent &amp; discerpant injusto aut iniquo bello, sed Gregem Christi pascant, &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia ad publicam honesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem &amp; tranquillitatem spectantia inquirant &amp; agant, ita administrantes praesentia ne amittant bona futura.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:45356:212"/>
               <head>Exaudi nos precan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Domine De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Jesu Christi &amp; misericordia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Pater.</head>
               <p>Pro Episcopis, Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteris, atque omni Clero, ut fide sanctâ &amp; moribus integris, homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis &amp; Exemplo, bene agendo &amp; patienter ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la tolerando, pascant &amp; enutriant populum Dei, ut ad Patriam caelestem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitent, ducant, &amp; ipsl praeeant, sectas minnant
<pb facs="tcp:45356:213"/> &amp; rectè instruant, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticula &amp; impiorum caetus armis spiritualibus dissipent &amp; disturbent, &amp; post uberem conversio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem animarum sicut stel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loe resplendeant in orbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus aeternae claritatis.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Exaudi nos precan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Pro uxore &amp; liberis &amp; totâ familiâ, ut illis tu bone Deus salutem mentis &amp; corporis largi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aris, ut sufficiens ad iter
<pb facs="tcp:45356:213"/> coeleste perficiendum mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistres viaticum tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rale, ut ab omni malo cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stodias, dirigas, &amp; tuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, &amp; sanctifices, ut si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus conjugati cum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sto, te Patrem aeternum, clementem &amp; misericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem habeamus, &amp; ut si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus familia Sancta, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegro officio nostro functi, tandem jure adoptivo in familiam tuam in civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Sanctâ haeredes as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciscamur.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:45356:214"/>
               <head>Exaudi nos precan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>Pro fratribus, ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, &amp; Benefactori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus: corporibus corum Angelos deputes custodes, animabus Spiritum San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum Ducem, necessitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus eorum providentiam tuam curatricem &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrum, atque eos ab ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternâ damnatione gratia tua eripiat &amp; conservet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:45356:214"/>
               <head>Exaudi nos precan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>Pro omni statu &amp; differentia Christiani Populi. Praesta Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Rex aeterne, Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus castitatem, Deo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catis continentiam, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugatis fidem &amp; Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniam, Viduis &amp; Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanis tutelam, Pauperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus sustentationem, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regrinantibus Angelum Comitem, &amp; pium &amp; fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licem reditum, Navigan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus portum, Lugentibus
<pb facs="tcp:45356:215"/> consolationem, Oppressis patrocinium, Afflictis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientiam &amp; liberatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, Martyribus &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessoribus fidem, perseve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiam, &amp; retributio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem coelestis brabii; poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentibus indulgentiam, Optimis Sanctitatem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defessam &amp; denuò dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam, mediocribus pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis &amp; Religionis au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctarium, delinquentibus correctionem, &amp; resipis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiam opportunam &amp; tempestivam; aegris tu compone lectum, &amp; da
<pb facs="tcp:45356:215"/> resignatum &amp; patientem animum, &amp; ut tibi pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuerit, atque illis expedit, sanitatem aut mortem Sanctam &amp; beatam; scrupulosis fidem corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, &amp; intellectum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strue, Dubitantibus tu te Praesta Ducem &amp; Docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem; Condemnatis ad mortem da solatium, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem &amp; quietum spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, charitate &amp; gratiâ plenum; libertatem cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivis, inimicis gratiam charitatis &amp; poeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, omnibus fidelibus
<pb facs="tcp:45356:216"/> pro variis suis necessita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus requiem, refrigeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, &amp; tandem misericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam in die tremendi Judicii.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Exaudi nos precan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>Custodi (Bone De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us) Magistratus in justitiâ, Coelum in Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>britate, terram in uber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, populum tuum à fame, &amp; peste, ab incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio domus, à diluvio &amp; vivicomburio personas, à
<pb facs="tcp:45356:216"/> fragio &amp; Exilio, à car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere &amp; caede, à viduita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te &amp; orbitate, à violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ poenarum &amp; passio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, à tempestatibus &amp; terrae motu, à nimiâ solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citudine &amp; impatientiâ, à taedio animi &amp; despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione, à morte impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visà inopportunâ &amp; gravi, maledictâ, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solenti, ab improvisis ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentibus, à metu ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mio, ab omni irâ tuâ, &amp; ab omni omnimodò pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato.</p>
               <p>Nationes belligeras re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prime,
<pb facs="tcp:45356:217"/> errantes converte, alienatas advoca, popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum tuum indies Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fica, infantes ad virilem aetatem perducas, noviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os confirma, Catechume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos instrue, praegnantibus tu partum felicem lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gire, &amp; nos omnes in regnum coelorum congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga:</p>
               <p rend="indent">Tu dirige viam nostram, tuere vitam, serva nos in timore, largire pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem viae, &amp; haeredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem Patriae, per Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum
<pb facs="tcp:45356:217"/> Christum Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Nostrum. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pater noster,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu are desir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that rhere is a piece lately Printed of Mr. <hi>Ioh. Quarles,</hi> Entituled <hi>Divine Meditations</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on several Subjects, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise a Coment on the Times, Written by <hi>Thomas Wall,</hi> Mr. in Arts: And are to be sold by <hi>John Stafford,</hi> at his House in <hi>George-yard,</hi> neer <hi>Fleet-bridge,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:45356:218"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>I S</p>
                  <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:45356:218"/>
            <head>Dr. <hi>Hewit</hi> His Last PRAYER.</head>
            <p>O Most glorious Lord God, thou whose dwelling is so far above the highest heavens, that thou humblest thy self but to look upon the things that are in heaven, and that are in Earth, thou who dost whatsoever thou wilt both in Heaven, in Earth, in the Sea, and in all places. In thy hands are the hearts of all men, and thou turnest them which way soever thou
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45356:219"/> wilt. O Lord! look in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and compassion, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee, on this great and numerous people of this Land with an eye of pitty, not with an eye of fury and indignation; O look not on al <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hose great and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous sins that have provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thee most justly to wrath &amp; displeasure against us. But gracious God! who can stand in thy sight when thou art angry? when thou with rebuke dost correct man for sin, thou makst his beauty to consume away like as it were a Moth fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a Garment. O Lord!
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45356:219"/> thy indignation and wrath lies heavy upon us, &amp; thou hast vexed us with scour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, thou hast made us a reproach and a by-word amongst our Neighbours, and the very heathen laugh us to scorn. Oh that thou wouldest turn us again, O Lord God of Hosts! that thou wouldst shew us the light of thy countenance, that we may behold it; that thou wouldst humble us for al those sins &amp; grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous transgressions that are amongst us; for those Atheisms, for those infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, horrid Blasphemies,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45356:220"/> &amp; Prophaneness, for those Sacriledges for those Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, for those Schisms, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, &amp; al those blindnesses of heart, pride, vain-glory and hypocrisie, that leads us from thee, it perswades us it will bring us to thee; O humble us for that envy, hatred and malice, and all uncharitableness, that hath set us one against another, that we are so dashed one against another, even to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy each other; <hi>Ephraim</hi> against <hi>Manasseh</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasseb</hi> against <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and both against <hi>Judah.</hi> This thou hast done to us to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45356:220"/> make us a scourge unto each other, O Lord because we have rebelled against thee: O how greatly and grievously have we sinned? yet for al this, thou hast not requited us according to our ill deservings, for thou mightest have brought us to desolation and destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: fire might have come down from heaven and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed us; our forraign Enemies, and the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of thee, and thy Christ our Saviour, might have swallowed us up. What have we not deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? yet O the long-suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and patience, &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45356:221"/> of our God! O Lord our God! we pray thee that thy patience and long-suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering might lead us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, that thou wouldst be pleased thou who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightest not in the death of a sinner, but rather that he should turn from his sins and live, that thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est turn us unto thee, O Lord! &amp; we shal be turned: draw us, &amp; we shall run af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thee: draw us with the Cords of love, and by the hands of thy loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, by the powerfull working of thy holy spirit in our souls, work contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45356:221"/> in our hearts, and a godly sorrow for all our sins, even a sorrow to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and a repentance to salvation never to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of, O Lord break these stony hearts of ours by the hammer of thy word, mollifie them by the oyle of thy Grace, smite these rockie hearts of ours by the Rod of thy most gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious power, that we may shed forth Rivers of tears for the sins we have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. O that thou wouldst make us grieve, because we cannot grieve; and to weep because we cannot weep
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45356:222"/> enough: that thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est humble us more &amp; more in the true sight and sense of all our provocations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thee, and that thou wouldest be pleased in the blood of Jesus Christ, to cleanse us from al our sins; Lord let his blood that speaks beter things then that of <hi>Abel,</hi> cry louder in thine ears for mercy, then al those mischiefes &amp; wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednesses that have been done amongst us for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. O besprinkle my polluted, but penitent soul, in the blood of Jesus Christ that I may be clean in thy
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45356:222"/> sight, and that the light of thy countenance may shine upon me. Lord! be pleased to seal unto mine, &amp; al our soules, the free pardon of al our sins, and say that we may heare it, that thou art well-pleased with us, and appeased towards us. Lord! do thou by thy spirit as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure our spirits, that we are thy Children, &amp; that thou art reconciled to us in the blood of Jesus Christ. To this end, O Lord! create in us new hearts, and renew right spirits within us: cast us not away from thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, &amp; take not thy holy spirit from us; but give us
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45356:223"/> the comfort of thy help, &amp; establish us with thy free spirit. Help us to live as thy redeemed ones, and (Lord!) let us not any longer by our wicked lives deny that most holy faith whereof our lips have so long time made profession but let us that call on the name of the Lord Jesus, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from iniquity, &amp; hate every evil way. Help us to cast away all our transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, whereby we have transgressed, and make us new hearts. Carry us along through the Pilgrimage, of this world, supplying us
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45356:223"/> with all things needfull for us; thy grace alone is sufficient for us: Lord! let thy grace be assistant to us, to strengthen us against all the temptation of Satan, especially against those sins whereunto we are most prone, either by custome or constitution, or most ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily provoked to. O Lord! with what affliction soever thou shalt punish, do not punish us with spirituall judgments and desertions. Give us not over to our own hearts lusts, to our vile lewd, &amp; corrupt affection, Give us not over to hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45356:224"/> and impenitency of heart, but make us sensible of the least sin, and give us thy grace to think no sin little; committed against thee our God, but that we may be humbled for it, and repent of it, and reform it in our lives and conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: and Lord! keep us fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m presumptious sins, O let not them get the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over us, but keep us innocent from the great of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences. And Lord! sanctifie unto us all thy methods &amp; proceedings with us, fitting us for all further tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; tryals whatsoever
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45356:224"/> thou in thy divine pleasure shalt be pleased to impose upon us: Lord give us pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, constancy, resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and fortitude to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go them, that though we walk through the valley of the shadow of death, we may fear none il: knowing that thou, O Lord! art mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully with us, and that with thy rod as well as with thy staff, thou wilt support and comfort us; &amp; that nothing shall be able to separate us from thy love which is in Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
            <p>And (gracious God!) we
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45356:225"/> beseech thee be thou pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to look mercifully and compassionately on thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Catholique Church, and grant that all they that do confesse thy holy Name, may agree together in the truth of thy holy Word, &amp; live in unity &amp; godly love. Thou hast promised, O Lord! The gates of hell shall not prevaile against thy Church: performe, we beseech thee, thy most gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promises, both to thy whole Church, and to that part of it which thou hast planted, and now afflicted in these sinfull Lands, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45356:225"/> Nations wherein we live. Arise, O Lord! &amp; have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon our Sion, for it is time that thou have mercy upon her; yea, the time is come for thy servants think upon her stones; and it pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth them to see her in the dust. Lord! maintain thine own Cause; rescue the light of thy truth from all those clouds of errours and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies which do so much obscure it, and let the light thereof in a free profession break forth &amp; shine again among us, and that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, even as long as the Sun and Moon endures.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:45356:226"/>
            <p>And gracious God! look mercifully upon all our Relations, &amp; do thou bring them to the light of thy Truth, that are wandring and ready to fal, that grace here may interest them in glory hereafter. Confirme them in thy Truth that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready stand: Shew some good token for good unto them, that they may rejoyce. O let thy good hand of providence be over them in all their wayes: &amp; to all orders and degrees of men that be amongst us. Give religious hearts to them that now rule in Authority
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45356:226"/> over us: Loyall hearts in their Subjects towards their Supreame: &amp; loving hearts in all men to their Friends, &amp; charitable hearts one towards another. And for the continuance of thy Gospel among us, restore in thy good time to their severall Places &amp; Callings, and give grace, O Heavenly Father! to all Bishops, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors &amp; Curates, that they may both by their Life &amp; Doctrine set forth thy true and lively word, &amp; rightly &amp; duly administer thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament. And Lord! blesse thy Church stil with
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45356:227"/> Pastors after thine own heart, with a continual suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of faithful and able men, that they may both by Life &amp; Doctrine declare thy Truth, and never for fear or favour back-slide or depart from the same. And give them the assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of thy spirit that may inable them so to preach thy word, that they may keep thy people upright in the midst of a corrupted &amp; corrupt generation. And, good Lord! bless thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple every where with hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eares, understanding hearts, conscientious souls,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45356:227"/> and obedient lives, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally those over whom I have had either lately or formerly a charge, that with meek hearts and due reverence, they may hear &amp; receive thy holy word, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly serving thee in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness and holiness al the days of our lives.</p>
            <p>And we beseech thee of thy goodness, O Lord! to comfort and succour all those that in this transito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry life be in trouble, sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, need, sickness, or any other adversity; Lord! help the helpless, comfort the comfortless, visit the sick,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45356:228"/> releive the oppressed, help them to right that suffer wrong, set them at liberty that are in Prison, restore the banished, and of thy great mercy; &amp; in thy good time deliver all thy people out of their necessities: Lord! do thou of thy great mercy fit us al for our lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end: for the hour of death and the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and do thou in the hour of death, and at the day of Judgment, from thy wrath &amp; everlasting dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, good Lord deliver us, through the Cross and passion of our Lord <hi>Jesus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:45356:228"/>
            <p>In the mean time; O Lord! teath us so to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our days, and me my Minutes, that we may apply our hearts to true wisdom, that we may be wise unto salvation, that we may live soberly, godly and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously, in this present world denying all ungodliness &amp; worldly lusts: Lord! teach us so to live, that we may not be a fraid to dye, and that we may so live that we may be alwayes prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to die, that when death shall seize upon us it may not surprise us, but that we may lift up our heads with
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45356:229"/> joy, knowing that our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption draws nigh, and that we shall be for ever happy, being assured that we shall come to the felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Chosen, &amp; rejoyce with the gladness of thy people: and give us such a fulness of thy holy Spirit that may make us stedfa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in this faith; and confirme us in this hope; indue me with patience under thy afflicting hand, and let not death be unpleasing to me, but support me in this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitation, that I may dye with a confidence to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come death, and so to live
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45356:229"/> for ever, and so fortifie my soul with the assistance of thy spirit, that I may to the last minute be assisted with a most chearful resolution to give up my self to thy divine disposing, that so passing the pilgrimage of this world, we may come to the Land of Promise, the Heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> that we may reign with thee in the World to come, through Jesus Christ our Lord; in whose blessed Name and Words we further call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, saying.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t thy mighty hand and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45356:230"/> out-stretched arme, O Lord! be the defence of me, and all other thy servants, thy mercy &amp; loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, in <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> our sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, thy true and holy Word, our instruction, thy Grace and holy Spirit, our comfort and consolation, to the end, and in the end, through <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> our Lord, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <p>Choice Forms of Prayer.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>